<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An historical account, and defence [sic], of the canon of the New Testament In answer to Amyntor.</title>
            <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52612</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1507A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216541</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828268</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828268</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32695</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52612)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32695)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1856:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An historical account, and defence [sic], of the canon of the New Testament In answer to Amyntor.</title>
                  <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-122, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J. Darby, for Andrew Bell, at the Cross-Keys and Bible in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DCC. [1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed Stephen Nye.</note>
                  <note>Amyntor is by John Toland. "An abstract of the foregoing disputation." (p.113) seems to be a summary of Amyntor's arguments.</note>
                  <note>With two final adverisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Contains running title "A defence of the canon of the New Testament.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Christ Church Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Toland, John, 1670-1722. --  Amyntor.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T --  Canon.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32695:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN HISTORICAL ACCOUNT, AND DEFENCE, OF THE CANON OF THE New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to AMYNTOR.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The weaker-ſighted ever look too nigh;</l>
               <l>But their Diſputes the Sacred Page make good:</l>
               <l>As doubted Tenures, which <hi>long Pleadings try,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Authentick grow; by being much withſtood.</l>
               <bibl>By Sir William Davenant, in Gondib.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by J. Darby, for Andrew Bell at the Croſs-Keys and Bible in Cornhil. M.DCC.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:32695:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:32695:2"/>
            <head>AN HISTORICAL ACCOUNT, AND DEFENCE, OF THE <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AT the Suggeſtion of a Learned Friend; I am about to anſwer to a Book, <hi>Amyntor;</hi> dedicated, to very formidable Patrons. For in his Title Page, the Author makes this addreſs.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Dî quibus imperium Animarum eſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſilentes,</l>
               <l>Et Chaos, &amp; Phlegethon, loca, nocte tacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia latè;</l>
               <l>Sit mihi fas audita loqui: ſit <hi>Numine veſtro,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Pandere res <hi>altâ terrâ &amp; caligine</hi> merſis.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:32695:3"/>
            <p>We may Engliſh it, thus.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ye Gods and Ghoſts of <hi>Hell,</hi> to Human ſight</l>
               <l>Not yet reveal'd, and thou whole Realm of <hi>Night,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Protect me; that I ſafely may relate</l>
               <l>The <hi>blacker</hi> Secrets of our Church, and State.</l>
            </q>
            <p>There will not want thoſe, who will ſay hereupon: From praying, to the Holy Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and the Saints; <hi>Amyntor</hi> is improved, into invoking the Devil and his Angels. They will ſay, he is the firſt, that ever pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licly put himſelf, under ſuch a Protection. That however, a Book directed againſt the Sacred Canon, would not eaſily find other Patrons: So that this Extravagance of the Author, was as much the Effect, of Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; as of Inclination. In ſhort, I wiſh, he had not given occaſion to his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to jeſt upon him; for what (I believe) was not deſign, but obreption and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, he preſents us with a Catalogue of Antient Books, and other Writings; concerning which, he is of a different (and contrary) mind, in divers parts of his Book.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:32695:3"/>
            <p>Sometimes, he ſeems to complain, that we do not receive 'em into the Canon of the New Teſtament; there being (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him) the ſame Reaſons to admit, or to exclude them, as for the Goſpels, Epiſtles, and other Writings of our Canon. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſo many of 'em were Cited by the Fathers, as Scripture; and the reſt, by very conſiderable Parties of Chriſtians: which (he ſaith again) is as much as can be alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for any of the Books of our Canon; and more than can be truly ſaid, for divers of them. But otherwhile, he ſpeaks to this Effect: That they are the <hi>Forgeries,</hi> partly of zealous Bigots; who were ſollicitous to provide theſe Crutches, for lame Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: and partly of ſome Heathens, that were tickl'd with the pleaſure of impoſing on the (known) ſimplicity, and credulity, of the firſt Chriſtians; who were wont to ſwallow any Book as Divine Revelation, if it had but a great many Miracles, ſprinkled with a few good Morals.</p>
            <list>
               <head>He hath diſpoſed theſe Books, under the following Titles, and Diſtinctions.</head>
               <item>I. Books, reported to be written by Chriſt himſelf, or that particularly concern him. His Letter, in anſwer to that of <hi>Abgarus,</hi> King of <hi>Edeſſa.</hi> A Letter to <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:32695:4"/>His Parables and Sermons. A Hymn, which he ſecretly taught to his Apoſtles and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piles. A Book of the Magic of Chriſt; if it be not the ſame with the Epiſtle to <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> A Book of the Nativity of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, of the Holy Virgin his Mother, and her Midwife. But he believes, this laſt is the ſame with the Goſpel of <hi>James.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. By the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or concerning her. Her Epiſtle to <hi>Ignatius.</hi> Her Letter to the Inhabitants of <hi>Meſſina.</hi> Her Book concerning the Miracles of Chriſt, and the Ring of King <hi>Solomon.</hi> A Book of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and another of her Death.</item>
               <item>III. By St. <hi>Peter. Peter</hi>'s Goſpel, Acts, Revelation, Doctrine, Judgment, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Liturgy, Itinerary; being ſo many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Books: but the laſt, he things, is the ſame with the Recognitions of St. <hi>Clement;</hi> wherein we have a very particular account of <hi>Peter</hi>'s Voyages and Performances. An Epiſtle of <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Clement.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IV. By St. <hi>Andrew.</hi> His Goſpel, and Acts.</item>
               <item>V. By St. <hi>James.</hi> A Liturgy, and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. His Book concerning the Death of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32695:4"/>Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> but there are Reaſons (he ſaith) to believe, <hi>John</hi> was author of it, not <hi>James.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VI. By St. <hi>John.</hi> His Acts, Liturgy, Iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerary, and Traditions. Another Goſpel, different from ours. His Book of the Death of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> mentioned twice al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</item>
               <item>VII. By St. <hi>Philip.</hi> The Goſpel of <hi>Philip,</hi> the Acts of <hi>Philip.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VIII. By St. <hi>Bartholomew.</hi> A Goſpel.</item>
               <item>IX. By St. <hi>Thomas.</hi> A Goſpel, Acts, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, and Itinerary; as alſo a Book of the Infancy of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>X. By St. <hi>Matthew.</hi> A Liturgy. There is alſo another by <hi>Mark.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XI. By St. <hi>Thaddaeus.</hi> A Goſpel.</item>
               <item>XII. By St. <hi>Matthias.</hi> A Goſpel, and Traditions.</item>
               <item>XIII. By St. <hi>Paul. Paul</hi>'s Revelation, and Preaching; his <hi>Anabaticon,</hi> and Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive concerning the charming of Vipers. His Epiſtle to the <hi>Laodiceans;</hi> his Second
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32695:5"/>Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians;</hi> his Third to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> and (again) to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> his Goſpel. His Epiſtles to <hi>Seneca;</hi> his Acts. The Acts alſo of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Thecla.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XIV. Other Goſpels and Remarkable Books. The prophetical Goſpel of <hi>Eve,</hi> the Goſpel of the Twelve Apoſtles, the Goſpels of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> the Goſpel of <hi>Judas Iſcariot.</hi> The Books of <hi>Adam,</hi> the Prophecy of <hi>Enoch;</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, and Aſtrology of <hi>Abraham.</hi> The Teſtament of the twelve Patriarchs, the Aſſumption of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Book of <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad,</hi> the Pſalms of King <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Viſion of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> the Revelation of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XV. Some other general Pieces. The Apoſtles Creed. The Doctrine of the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles; there are, beſides, Doctrines attributed to every one of the Apoſtles ſingly, and alſo to their Companions and immediate Succeſſors. The Doctrines of the twelve Apoſtles compoſed (by them) with the aſſiſtance of St. <hi>Paul.</hi> The Canons and Conſtitutions of the Apoſtles. The Acts of the Apoſtles, written by themſelves. The Goſpel of Perfection; the Precepts of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> The Itinerary of all the Apoſtles, as well as of every one of them ſingly, was formerly extant.</item>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:32695:5"/>
               <item>XVI. Writings of the Companions and Diſciples of the Apoſtles. The Epiſtles of <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> his Recognitions, Decretals, and other Pieces bearing his Name. The Epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius.</hi> An Epiſtle of <hi>Polycarp</hi> to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> with his other Writings: the Acts of the Martyrdom of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and of <hi>Polycarp.</hi> The Paſtor of <hi>Hermas,</hi> an Epiſtle of <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> the works of <hi>Dionyſins Areopagita:</hi> an Epiſtle of <hi>Marcellus</hi> (Diſciple of <hi>Peter</hi>) to <hi>Nereus</hi> and <hi>Achilleus:</hi> his Treatiſe of the conflict of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus.</hi> The Life of St. <hi>John,</hi> by <hi>Prochorus;</hi> the Petition of <hi>Veronica</hi> to <hi>Herod,</hi> on behalf of Chriſt; the Paſſion of <hi>Timothy,</hi> by <hi>Polycrates;</hi> the Paſſion of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> in two Books, by <hi>Linus.</hi> Two Epiſtles of <hi>Martial of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſin;</hi> his Life by <hi>Aurelianus:</hi> the Goſpel of <hi>Nicodemus;</hi> the Hiſtory of the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Conflict, by <hi>Abdias;</hi> the Paſſion of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> by the Presbyters of <hi>Achaia.</hi> The Epiſtle of <hi>Evodius,</hi> entituled <hi>the Light;</hi> the Altercation of <hi>Jaſon</hi> and <hi>Papiſcus:</hi> the Acts of <hi>Titus,</hi> compoſed by <hi>Zena</hi> companion of <hi>Paul:</hi> with a multitude of other Acts and Paſſions. The Goſpel of <hi>Barnabas;</hi> the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Barnabas:</hi> the Epiſtles of <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> to the <hi>Britains.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:32695:6"/>
               <item>XVII. Pieces alledged in favor of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, which were forged under the names of Heathens. The works of <hi>Triſmegiſtus,</hi> and <hi>Aſclepius;</hi> the Books of <hi>Zoroaſter,</hi> and <hi>Hiſtaſpes,</hi> Kings in the Orient; the <hi>Sibyllin</hi> Oracles. A Letter of <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> to <hi>Tiberius;</hi> the ſpeech of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: the Epiſtle of <hi>Lentulus,</hi> giving a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Perſon of Chriſt. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles or Orders of <hi>Adrian, Antoninus Pius,</hi> and <hi>M. Aurelius,</hi> in favor of the Chriſtians; extant in <hi>Juſtin Martyr.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Upon this Catalogue, and from it, <hi>Amyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> makes divers (marvellous) Remarks, and Inferences; to this effect. The Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents reckned the Paſtor of <hi>Hermas,</hi> the Epiſtles of <hi>Barnabas,</hi> of <hi>Polycarp</hi> and <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> to be as good, as any part of the New Teſtament. And if, <hi>ſaith He again,</hi> theſe pieces are not Impoſtures; but were really <hi>theirs,</hi> whoſe name they bear: why are they not received into the Canon of Scripture; the Authors of them having been the Companions and Fellow-laborers of the Apoſtles, as well as St. <hi>Mark</hi> and St. <hi>Luke?</hi> If this quality was ſufficient, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title the two latter to Inſpiration; why ſhould it not do as much for the two firſt? And if this be not all the reaſon; pray, let
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32695:6"/>us know the true one: for <hi>I never heard of any other.</hi> The ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>Peter,</hi> the Epiſtles of <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Jude,</hi> the ſecond and third of <hi>John,</hi> the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and the Revelation, were not approved as Canonical; till after the time of <hi>Euſebius:</hi> therefore, why may not we alſo eſtabliſh the Epiſtles of <hi>Clemens,</hi> and of <hi>Barnabas;</hi> if indeed they be theirs?</p>
            <p>It may be, <hi>ſaith our Author,</hi> all the Books (particularly, all the Goſpels) in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Catalogue, were not ſpurious or forg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but rather, Genuine, and of right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Canon of Scripture: as in the dark Ages of Popery, divers Books were added to the Bible; ſo in the no leſs ignorant firſt Ages of Chriſtianity, other Books might be taken from it; becauſe they did not ſute with all the Opinions of the ſtrongeſt ſide. How many true, or falſe Goſpels were extant in <hi>Luke</hi>'s time, God knows: but that there were ſeveral, may be inferred from his own words. <q>
                  <hi>Many</hi> have taken in hand, to ſet forth a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thoſe things, which are believed among us; as <hi>they</hi> delivered 'em to us, who (from the beginning) were Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes, and Miniſters of the WORD <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1.1, 2, 3,</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Several Books (particularly Goſpels) of the before-recited Catalogue, were quoted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32695:7"/>by the moſt celebrated Fathers, <hi>ſays Amyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor;</hi> to prove important Points of the Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Religion: and this Teſtimony of thoſe Fathers, was the principal Reaſon, of our putting the Goſpels and Epiſtles, that are now approved and received, into the preſent Canon. <hi>Euſebius</hi> rejects the Acts, Goſpels, Preaching, and Revelation of <hi>Peter;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no Antient nor Modern Writer, ſays he, has quoted proofs out of them: on the ſame account, he rejects alſo the Goſpels of <hi>Thomas, Matthias,</hi> and ſuch like; as alſo the Acts of <hi>Andrew, John,</hi> and other Apoſtles, as ſpurious. But herein <hi>Euſebius</hi> was miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken; as appears, <hi>ſays our Author ſtill,</hi> by the Teſtimonies I have cited. Had <hi>Euſebius</hi> found any of Theſe Pieces, alledged by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Orthodox Writers; he would have owned them as part of the Scripture-Canon: but I have ſhown, proofs were quoted out of ſome of them; ſo that they may ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Canon, for all <hi>Euſebius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is certain, <hi>ſo he goes on;</hi> the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> the Epiſtles of <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Jude,</hi> the ſecond and third of <hi>John,</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Peter,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation,</hi> were doubted by the ſoundeſt of the Antients; and yet are received by the Moderns: I ſay therfore, by more than a parity of reaſon; the Preaching and Revelation of <hi>Peter</hi> were received by the Antients, and ought not to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32695:7"/>be rejected by the Moderns, if the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Antients (or Fathers) be a proper recommendation of Books.</p>
            <p>The Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> convened about the year 360, is the firſt Aſſembly in which the Canon of Scripture was eſtabliſht. In ſuch a variety of Books, they could not determine which were the true Monuments of the Apoſtles; but either by a particular <hi>Revelation,</hi> of which we hear not a word; or by the <hi>Teſtimony of their Predeceſſors:</hi> I have the ſame Teſtimony, for the Books I defend. He means, for the Preaching and Revelation of <hi>Peter,</hi> the Paſtor of <hi>Hermas,</hi> the Epiſtle of <hi>Barnabas;</hi> and divers Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels.</p>
            <p>He wiſhes, ſome qualified Perſon would endeavor, to extricate the erroneous out of theſe and ſuch like difficulties; that we may diſcover, by ſome <hi>infallible marks,</hi> in ſuch an extraordinary number of Books (all of them equally pretending to Divine Origin) which of them are <hi>the proper Rule:</hi> leſt we unhappily miſtake a falſe one, for the true.</p>
            <p>He tells us again, the Philoſopher <hi>Celſus</hi> exclaims againſt the liberty which Chriſtians had taken, of changing the firſt Writing of the Goſpel, three or four, or more times; that ſo they might deny whatſoever was urged againſt them, as retracted before. The <hi>Manichees,</hi> a very conſiderable Sect,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32695:8"/>ſhewed other Scriptures; and denied the <hi>Genuinneſs</hi> of the whole New Teſtament: particularly <hi>Fauſtus</hi> (a <hi>Manichee</hi>) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, the <hi>Teſtament of the Son</hi> is corrupted, by obſcure Perſons, who have put the Names of the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors, to falſe Goſpels, that are full of Miſtakes, and of contradictory Relations and Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. After the deceaſe of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, <hi>ſays the Manichee,</hi> a ſett of Half-Jews picked up (from Fame and flying Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports) a great many Lies and Errors; which they alſo publiſhed, under the names of the Apoſtles, and of thoſe that ſucceeded them. Add to all this, that; the <hi>Ebionites</hi> or <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarens,</hi> who were the oldeſt Chriſtians, had a different Copy (from ours) of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi>'s Goſpel. The <hi>Marcionites</hi> read the Goſpel of St. <hi>Luke</hi> very diverſly from us; the Goſpel of St. <hi>John</hi> was attributed to <hi>Cerinthus:</hi> all the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul</hi> were denied by ſome, a different Copy ſhown of them by others. It would be commendably done, <hi>he ſays,</hi> to prevent the Miſchievous Inferences, which Hereticks may draw from all this; and to remove the Scruples of doubting, but ſincere Chriſtians: as for his own part, if he is in any fault about theſe matters, it is not too much Incredulity; but that, it may be, he believes more Scripture than his Adverſaries. He gives hopes, he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32695:8"/>will write a Hiſtory of the Canon of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; the faireſt, nay the only one of the kind, that ever was penned.</p>
            <p>He concludes with an extract, as he ſaith, out of <hi>Mr. Dodwel;</hi> to this purpoſe. The Books of the New Teſtament lay hid in the Archives of Churches, and Desks of private Perſons; to whom they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: till the latter end of the Reign of the Emperor <hi>Trajan,</hi> or rather of <hi>Adrian;</hi> that is, till about the year after Chriſt 130. Even the latter Evangeliſts had not ſeen the Goſpels of the former; elſe St. <hi>Luke</hi> would never have given ſuch a different Genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of our Saviour, from that by St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> without the reaſon of ſo wide a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: nor would there be found in the other Evangeliſts ſo many <hi>apparent contradictions;</hi> as have haraſſed the Wits of Learned Men, almoſt ſince the firſt conſtitution of the Canon. St. <hi>Luke</hi> plainly intimates that, the Evangeliſts and Goſpels he had ſeen, were not furniſht with the relations they make, by Eye-witneſſes; as himſelf was. We have at this day, ſays <hi>Mr. Dodwel,</hi> ſome writings of <hi>Ignatius, Polycarp, Hermas, Barnabas, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Romanus;</hi> theſe were later than the other Writers of the New Teſtament, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Jude</hi> and <hi>John:</hi> and yet <hi>Hermas</hi> cites nothing out of the New Teſtament; nor in all the reſt, are any of the Evangeliſts nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32695:9"/>If they cite any paſſages, like to thoſe we read in our preſent Goſpels; they are withal ſo unlike, that it cannot be known, whether they are alledged out of ours, or ſome Apocryphal Goſpels: they cite alſo Paſſages which are not in the preſent Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels. Nay, we cannot ſay from thoſe <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Books</hi> that were laſt written, that; the Church knew any thing of the Goſpels, or that the Clergy made a common uſe of them. We can't tell, whence St. <hi>Paul</hi> had that moral Aphoriſm of our Saviour; which he quotes, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.35. In thoſe early times, the true Writings of the Apoſtles uſed to be bound up, together with thoſe now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Apocryphal</hi> and <hi>Spurious;</hi> that it was not manifeſt, by any mark or public Cenſure of the Church, Which of them ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the other.</p>
            <p>Upon this judgment made by <hi>Mr. Dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel, Amyntor</hi> ſays; he agrees with <hi>Mr. Dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> as to matter of Fact. And he ſhuts up all, with adding, that; whoſoever has an inclination to write on this Subject, is now furniſht with a great many, curious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions; whereon to ſhow his Penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Judgment. As how the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Succeſſors and Diſciples of the Apoſtles, could ſo groſly confound the genuine Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of their Maſters; with ſuch as are falſly attributed to them? And if they were in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32695:9"/>the dark about theſe matters, in thoſe early times; How came the following Ages by a better Light? Why all thoſe Books, which are cited by <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> and the reſt, ſhould not be accounted equally <hi>authentic?</hi> And laſtly, What ſtreſs can we lay, on the Writings of thoſe Fathers; who not only contradict one another, but are alſo inconſiſtent with themſelves, in their relations of the very ſame Facts?</p>
            <p>The whole amounts, to thus much. <q>The Books we now own as Canonical, were never ſeen; till about 130 years after Chriſt: and when they appeared, 'twas not poſſible to diſtinguiſh them, but by ſome <hi>Revelation;</hi> from Apocryphal Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels and Epiſtles, which bore the names (as theſe do) of the Apoſtles and their Synergiſts. From the earlieſt times, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> Copies of them were ſhown; and not one of them but was rejected, by conſiderable and potent Parties of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians: the very Parties that received them, have changed 'em three or four, or more times; that they might be at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to affirm or deny, as preſent Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence ſhould require. The Figments of <hi>Hermas,</hi> the Traſh of <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and others ſuch like, have an equal right to a place in the Canon of Scripture; with the Goſpels of <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Luke.</hi> The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32695:10"/>and Credit of both, and of all the other Canonical and Extra-canonical Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, depending, on the Quotations made from them, by St. <hi>Ireneus, Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus, Origen,</hi> and one or two more of the Antients: and on their having been Contemporaries and Coadjutors to the Apoſtles.</q> And ſo in few words, Friends, <hi>bonas noctes</hi> to the Chriſtian Religion. Our Author however, that we may not forget to do him that right, is a compleat Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: tho he has us, and our Canon, at theſe Advantages; he ſaith, <hi>He will deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine nothing, but ſuſpend his Judgment.</hi> P. 58.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:32695:10"/>
               <head>On the <hi>CATALOGUE</hi> in general.</head>
               <p>THE Catalogue, by <hi>Amyntor,</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable on divers accounts:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As it is pretty Perfect.</hi> He has omitted but few, of thoſe Antient Pieces; and not ſo often miſtaken, as ſome others, the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and like Titles of the ſame Book, for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral and diſtinct Books.</p>
               <p>And, <hi>as it naturally gives one, a great Idea of the Chriſtian Religion.</hi> By informing us of ſo many Perſons that wrote Goſpels, Acts, Revelations, Liturgies, Itineraries, Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; either on their own knowledg, or on credible report made to them: and which have not been loſt on any other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, but ſuch as are common to things <hi>Valuable,</hi> and <hi>Great</hi> in their kind. Such as, the Deluge of (an immenſe) time, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 1700 years; the abſolute <hi>Certainty,</hi> and apparent <hi>Sufficiency,</hi> of the Goſpels, Acts, Epiſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which (on thoſe accounts) the Church has preſerved, and contents her ſelf with them.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, <hi>As nothing can be objected to it, or inferred from it; but what in ſuch a caſe a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32695:11"/>man (of any Experience or Prudence) would certainly expect.</hi> Namely that, in ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and various a Subject, there would be ſome more Writers and Writings; than the extreme Caution of the Catholic Church, would intirely approve: and even that ſome Triflers, and Impoſtors, would intermix and intrude themſelves, among the approved and well-meaning. It will be requiſite, to enlarge a little, on theſe general Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>That, <hi>the Catalogue is indifferent perfect,</hi> I grant. However, ſome Books (and other Writings) are omitted; and others, never really extant, or pretended to be extant, are added. For inſtance; under the <hi>firſt</hi> Head, or <hi>of Books aſcribed to our Saviour, or that particularly concern him;</hi> theſe are overlookt.</p>
               <p>A Book by St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> diſtinct from that by <hi>Thomas,</hi> concerning the Infancy of our Saviour; being the Hiſtory of his younger Years. 'Tis very antient; for it hath ſome Paſſages, that are alſo mentioned by St. <hi>Ireneus:</hi> and which, he ſaith, were in the Books ſhown by the <hi>Valentinians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Letter of our Saviour; that fell down from Heaven: it being indeed an Epiſtle, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by a certain notable Enthuſiaſt, a <hi>French</hi> Biſhop; who for this, and ſome other ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Facts, was deprived and put to penance,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32695:11"/>by a Council aſſembled at <hi>Rome,</hi> An. 745. The Letter however was kept in the Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, by order of Pope <hi>Zechary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Liturgy of our Saviour; received as his, by the <hi>Ethiopians:</hi> it was brought out of the Orient, by Father <hi>J. Vanſlebius;</hi> who promiſes alſo to publiſh it at <hi>Paris,</hi> together with other rare <hi>Ethiopic</hi> Pieces. But <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphus,</hi> in his Ethiopic Hiſtory and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary, gives the true account of this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As to Books added,</hi> under the ſame Head; <hi>Amyntor</hi> miſtakes when, as from <hi>Euſebius,</hi> he attributes to our Saviour <hi>a Book of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Sermons.</hi> For, on the contrary, theſe <hi>Proverbs</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> calls them) were all of them <hi>only Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal:</hi> they were Doctrines and Proverbs that <hi>Papias</hi> (Biſhop of <hi>Hierapolis</hi>) had heard from ſome Perſons, that they were ſpoke and taught by Jeſus Chriſt; but they never were committed to writing, as a particular Book, by any body. The <hi>Millennium,</hi> or thouſand-years Reign, was one of theſe Traditional Doctrines.</p>
               <p>I obſerve alſo that, <hi>Amyntor</hi> very often confirms the Books of his Catalogue, by witneſs of Authors who never mention any ſuch Book or Books; but only are thought by ſome, and that not very probably, to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32695:12"/>allude to them, or to have made uſe of them. When he gives us that non-ſuch Hiſtory of the Scripture-Canon, I hope, he will oftner <hi>himſelf conſult the Authors he cites;</hi> and leſs truſt to the References of others: elſe it will be far from meriting the praiſes, he has before-hand given to it.</p>
               <p>I incline to think, the Books wrote by the Apoſtles, their Contemporaries, and Synergiſts, are vaſtly more than <hi>Amyntor,</hi> or any other <hi>now,</hi> can give us the Titles, or other Traces of them: St. <hi>Ireneus</hi> calls them, Lib. 1. c. 17. <hi>In-enarrabilem multitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem Apocryphorum;</hi> an innumerable multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Apocryphal Books. For we are not to conſider all Authors and Books as Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal; that are cenſur'd, under thoſe names, by <hi>Ireneus:</hi> I am of opinion, we may apply to St. <hi>Ireneus;</hi> arguing againſt the <hi>Gnoſtics, Valentinians,</hi> and other Antient Sects and Books, that platonized too much; what, <hi>C. Rhodiginus</hi> (<hi>Lect, Antiq.</hi> § 1. c. 12.) ſays of <hi>Lactantius,</hi> and the Platoniſts. <hi>Ea, quae obvelatis traduntur figuris, a Platonicis; nec niſi Allegoricis enarrationibus intelligenda: iſte ut ſimpliciter dicta accepit. Oblitus, nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam futurum Platonicum, qui non putet Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonem allegoricè intelligendum.</hi>
                  <q>What the Platoniſts have delivered in dark, and figurative expreſſions; and muſt not be interpreted, but only in the Allegorical
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32695:12"/>way: that, he has underſtood, as ſpoken <hi>directly,</hi> and abſolutely; forgetting, or not knowing that, a man ſhall never be a Platoniſt, who imagines <hi>Plato</hi> is to be taken, not allegorically, but literally.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But this great number of Acts, Goſpels, Itineraries, Revelations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as I ſaid, be ſure <hi>they give Authority, and Luſtre, to the Chriſtian Religion.</hi> As we came hereby to underſtand, it was an extraordinary Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure that Chriſtianity made in the World, at its very firſt appearance. It ſhould ſeem, men thought, they had never wrote enough concerning it: its admirable Morals, the Miracles of its Author and other firſt Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of it, its Revelations and Prophecies, verified by almoſt an immediate completi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did ſo convince and affect 'em; that they even filled the world with their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of theſe things, under the names of <hi>Acts, Revelations, Itineraries, Epiſtles, Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, Martyrdoms, Liturgies, Precepts, Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, Inſtitutions, Oracles,</hi> and ſome more. 'Tis of ſome of theſe, that St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaks in the firſt Verſes of his Goſpel. He meant not the Goſpel of <hi>John;</hi> for 'tis agreed on all hands, <hi>John</hi> wrote his Goſpel long after the other Evangeliſts, and to ſupply ſome of their Omiſſions. That he did not intend, only <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark;</hi> who indeed wrote before him; may be inferred from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32695:13"/>his own words, when he ſays. <q>Not, τινὲς, <hi>ſome,</hi> one or two; but πολλὸι, MANY have taken in hand to ſet forth a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thoſe things, that are moſt ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed among us; even as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered them unto us, who <hi>from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning were Eye-witneſſes,</hi> and Miniſters of the WORD.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amyntor</hi> and <hi>M. Dodwel</hi> believe St. <hi>Luke</hi> doth not ſpeak of the Goſpels of <hi>John, Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark;</hi> they ſuppoſe, he had not ſo much as ſeen any of thoſe Goſpels. But what is in their mind, to tell us that; <q>
                     <hi>Luke</hi> plainly intimates, the Authors of the Goſpels which he had ſeen, had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted neither any Perſons that had been <hi>Eye-witneſſes;</hi> nor ſo much as thoſe who had ſeen or ſpoke with any ſuch: and that on theſe Accounts, the Credit of thoſe Goſpels, is ſuſpected and dubious.</q> For St. <hi>Luke,</hi> as before quoted, expreſly ſays; the Authors by him intended, had wrote concerning our Saviour, his Miracles and Doctrine, juſt in the manner <hi>as they deliver'd them to us, who from the beginning were Eye-witneſſes.</hi> He could not poſſibly have given a more ample Teſtimony, either to their Fidelity, or their Accuracy.</p>
               <p>In accounting for the Reaſons, why theſe Books are loſt; too many People have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſpeak with intolerable Effrontry, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32695:13"/>Profanity. I will firſt give the true Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of ſo great a loſs; and then examine the ſcurrilous Conjectures of ſome, who glory in their ſhame.</p>
               <p>In general; <q>I could never wonder, we have loſt ſo many of the Apoſtolic Writings, and other Antient (import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant) Monuments of the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſince I took notice, we have loſt alſo the very beſt Books of the Antients, in all parts of Learning and Science.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In Philoſophy; to the times of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, we have almoſt nothing left to us, but the Works of <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> the leaſt valuable, it may be, of all the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents. The Philoſophy of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> being little elſe, but ſome dry Definitions; that give no light to the Natures of things: and that of <hi>Plato,</hi> ſuch a futility in Philoſophy, as <hi>Behmeniſm</hi> in Religion and Chriſtianity; even a Rapſody of ſome Myſtical (or Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſical) Terms, ſprinkled here and there with a bright Thought, or lively Expreſſion.</p>
               <p>Of all the Philoſophical Writers; <hi>ſince our Saviour,</hi> there remain (in my preſent remembrance) only two or three <hi>Platoniſts</hi> and <hi>Stoics,</hi> that were <hi>Greecs;</hi> by the <hi>Latins,</hi> there are only (I think) ſome Natural Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by <hi>Seneca;</hi> and a few moral Pieces by the ſame <hi>Seneca,</hi> and by <hi>M. Cicero.</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy was cultivated, above 700 years,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32695:14"/>in <hi>ASIA;</hi> as alſo in <hi>Egypt, Greece, Italy,</hi> and moſt other Provinces of <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ROPE;</hi> in <hi>AFRICA,</hi> from <hi>Cyrene</hi> to the Pillars of <hi>Hercules</hi> and the Ocean, being one of the longeſt tracts of Ground in the World. It grew into ſuch reputation, that there were very many Academies; and an incredible number of Profeſſors and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, divers of them in high eſteem. But few Perſons of the better ſort, that did not cauſe their Children to be educated, in ſome of theſe Academies: even the principal No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, whether <hi>Greecs</hi> or <hi>Latins,</hi> after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bore the Chief Offices of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, did not diſdain to learn Philoſophy in their years, if they had miſſed it in their youth; nay a Nobleman was not eſteemed, if he were not a competent Orator and Philoſopher. We may be aſſured therefore, we have loſt a prodigious multitude of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Books, in the ſeveral parts of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy; wrote by the moſt Eminent Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, among the ſeveral Sects: undoubtedly it was then, as now, a cuſtomary thing; that, famous Profeſſors wrote ſomething, more or leſs, either led by their own Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or by occaſion of ſome Provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or perſwaded by their Scholars and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers. Who (as I ſaid but now) were all the Nobility; and all Perſons of Diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whether for Wealth or Wit.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:32695:14"/>
               <p>The like may be ſaid of Authors, and Books, concerning Aſtronomy, Aſtrology, Divination, Magic, Geometry, Mechanics, Medicine, Anatomy , Botanics, Poetry, Painting, Architecture, Statuary, the Origin and Rites of the Paganic Religions; Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, both Natural and Civil. <hi>Amyntor</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſomewhere puts us in mind, what is the Damage in the Hiſtorical part of Learning. <q>The loſs, <hi>ſays he,</hi> of ſo many Decads of the Roman Hiſtoriographer, <hi>T. Livius,</hi> is alone as much to be regretted; <hi>as if all the Fathers had miſcarried.</hi>
                  </q> 'Tis eaſy to gueſs the Reaſon, <hi>He was a Heathen, and they were Chriſtians.</hi> But we ſee however, by all this; that, the mere force, or edacity of time, bears away, or devours the moſt excellent Inſtances of Human Induſtry, and Wit: that we ought not to marvel, if we have not ſtill <hi>all,</hi> or even had not <hi>the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal</hi> Labors, of the Apoſtles, and Apoſtolical men. If <hi>Amyntor</hi>'s Catalogue of Books, ſome of them once reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enced by the Church, and now loſt, were much larger than it is: it would by no means prove, they were <hi>all</hi> Trivial, Spurious, or Erroneous Books; 'twould be no imputation on Chriſtianity, as abounding only with Fables and Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. There being, we have ſeen, no part of Learning (tho never ſo uſeful and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or ſo curious and diverting;) but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32695:15"/>has ſuffered extremely, by the loſs of ſome excellent Books and Authors, nay of moſt ſuch Authors and Books.</p>
               <p>I believe alſo, <q>The unqueſtionable <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxy;</hi> the yielded certainty, or <hi>genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inneſs;</hi> and apparent <hi>ſufficiency,</hi> of the preſent Scripture-Canon, were great Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations that the Books in the Catalogue, fell (gradually) into diſ-uſe, and were afterwards loſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>As to <hi>the ſufficiency</hi> of the Books of the Canon; I mean, of all them taken to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; it is ſelf-evident. For they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, a (repeated) Abrogation of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaic</hi> Law, ſo far as 'tis Ritual and Judicial; a compleat Syſtem, of Morals; the Hiſtory of the Parentage, Conception, Birth, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, Doctrine, Death, Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion of our Saviour: the deſcent of the Holy Spirit on the Apoſtles, their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſpiration, and Miraculous Powers; their Epiſtles, to private Perſons, to Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Nations; in which they often (profeſſedly) repeat the Subſtance of the Chriſtian Religion, as well in what reſpects <hi>Faith</hi> as <hi>Manners.</hi> In ſhort, a man cannot read theſe Books, without moſt plainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, that; they are ſuch an Account of the Religion they teach, as needs no Supplement.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:32695:15"/>
               <p>Their <hi>Genuinneſs,</hi> and <hi>Orthodoxy;</hi> or that they are the very Books of the Authors whoſe names they bear, and are true Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of the Doctrines of Chriſtianity <hi>as delivered to the Churches</hi> by the firſt (Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous) Preachers: this is inferred, with abſolute certainty, <hi>from their reception by all thoſe Churches, as ſuch;</hi> and that <hi>theſe,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Books of the Catalogue (tho divers of <hi>them</hi> alſo were highly valued) have been preſerved.</p>
               <p>If it be urged, that; ſuppoſing, as this Anſwer does, the Books in the Catalogue (moſt of them, or <hi>ſome</hi> of them) were <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and <hi>Genuine,</hi> and owned to be ſuch by the Churches: 'tis much, they ſhould be loſt; and only the Books of the preſent Canon preſerved. Which have been preſerved, it ſeems, for no <hi>other</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but what are common alſo to the Books of the Catalogue: namely, becauſe they are (undoubtedly) Orthodox, and (certainly) Genuine.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, that; the Books of the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue that are loſt, or rejected, were not <hi>ſo</hi> certainly Cenuin, to <hi>all</hi> the Churches; as thoſe that are preſerved, and made parts of the Canon. And as to the <hi>Orthodoxy,</hi> tho that (as to many of them) was not queſtioned; yet the Books not being ſo certain as to their Genuinneſs in all parts of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32695:16"/>the Chriſtian World, and therefore not allowed as (unexceptionable) Evidences in the numerous Controverſies that aroſe in the Catholic Church; and the un-ſuſpected Books being abundantly ſufficient to ſerve the ends of Religion, in reſpect both of Controverſy, and Inſtitution in manners: the former (hereupon) almoſt unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably began to be neglected, and in time were loſt; and only the latter were kept.</p>
               <p>We have now the advantages of Printing, and of a ready Communication (by the increaſe of Trade, and Improvement of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation) between Nation and Nation: the Antients wanted theſe helps; therefore with them, a Book concerning the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, if it were not publiſhed in <hi>Judea,</hi> or at <hi>Rome,</hi> or in ſome part of <hi>Greece;</hi> or ſome conſiderable City of <hi>Aſia,</hi> it might not come to be known of a long time; not vulgarly and generally known in the Churches, till the Evidences that it was Genuine were all wholly loſt, or become of but little Authority. The Books of our preſent Canon, were immediately commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated by the Churches, or Perſons, to whom they were written; unto all the Famous Churches. Like Induſtry was not uſed, on behalf of the Books of the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue; therefore theſe laſt were read only, or chiefly, in the places of their Publication,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:32695:16"/>and in the Churches to which they were addreſſed: and thus being long unknown to the Churches, and Illuſtrious Writers, of other places; tho many of them were approved as to their Doctrine and Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, on which accounts they are often quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by (thoſe two, the moſt Learned of the <hi>Antenicen</hi> Fathers) <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> and <hi>Origen,</hi> yet they did not obtain to be adopted into the Scripture-Canon; as not ſo certainly the Works of Apoſtles and Apoſtolical men, as thoſe that were received for ſuch <hi>every where,</hi> and <hi>from the beginning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Farther, it may be divers Books of the Catalogue, titled with the name of an Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, or Synergiſt of the Apoſtles, <q>were rejected (and in proceſs of time, loſt;) for that very reaſon.</q> It was ſuppoſed that, the Book having to it a name of one of the Apoſtle, or ſome Apoſtolical Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; therefore the Author claims to be that Perſon, or that Apoſtle: it might appear however, by ſome things in the Book it ſelf, or by ſome Circumſtances commonly known, that the Author was not the Apoſtle, or other Perſon vulgarly thought to be deſigned in the Title; and hereupon the Book was conſider'd as a Forgery and Impoſture, and as wrote (probably) with ſome diſhoneſt Intention and Aim. But as <hi>now,</hi> ſo <hi>then;</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32695:17"/>
                  <hi>then</hi> much more than <hi>now;</hi> abundance of People had the <hi>ſame names</hi> with the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and other firſt Preachers: it may be, moſt Chriſtians took thoſe Names, either at their Converſion, or Baptiſm. A Book therefore, (ſuppoſe a Goſpel, Epiſtles, Acts,) might really be the Work of the Author in the Title-page, or elſwhere in the Book; and yet in ſhort time be rejected, neglected, and finally loſt, as an Impoſture and Forgery, on <hi>that falſe ſuppoſition,</hi> that the Author affected to ſeem the Perſon that he was not, and that (in truth) he never pretended to be. This very thing hath cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly hapned, in divers Works of the Fathers; as well thoſe of the fourth and fifth Ages, and later, as thoſe of the ſecond and third: and it might happen, I ſay, in divers Writings of the Catalogue that we are conſidering.</p>
               <p>I take theſe to be ſome of the Cauſes, that ſo many Books of the Catalogue are loſt: Time; the Sufficiency of the Books preſerved; and <hi>that,</hi> ſome of them came not to general knowledg, till the Evidences that they were Genuine, were not ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. Theſe are ſuch Reaſons, and Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of it, that we cannot much wonder at the misfortune of this (invaluable) Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. And after this, 'tis but little to the credit of their Judgment, and <hi>leſs</hi> of their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:32695:17"/>Morals, that ſome affect to gueſs at the Cauſes of this Miſhap, in a ſort that reflects on the Chriſtian Religion; as if it had no manner of certainty, and that we cannot now (nor ever could) diſtinguiſh Fables and Impoſtures, from Authentic Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. If a man is diſpoſed, to employ his Wit in ſcurrilous Conjectures: he may ſay many things on ſuch a Subject as this, that ſhall be loudly applauded by the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſans of Scepticiſm and Profanity; and that will ſurpriſe the Superficial, tho they be Serious and well-diſpoſed. But I maintain, that; after we have diſcovered ſuch Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the loſs of theſe Books, as every body muſt allow that ſome of them are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and others of them are probable, and all of them conſiſtent with the reverence due to Religion: thoſe other (Sportive, or Malevolent) Conjectures will be inſiſted on, only by ſuch as affect to be Infidels; or that love to be vain, tho in a ſerious and weighty Subject, And tho to convince ſuch People, is (it may be) an impoſſible Task; it being ſo much in the power of the Mind, whether it will admit a light to which it has prejudices: yet it will not be hard, to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the Indifferent, that; thoſe Gueſſes are not the reſults of Judgment, but only of a ſceptical, abuſeful, prejudicate, and intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Partiality and Vanity.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:32695:18"/>
               <p>They tell us, theſe Books were not loſt, <hi>they were ſuppreſt,</hi> becauſe they contained ſome things, contrary to the Perſuaſions of the ſtrongeſt ſide; which always calls it ſelf the Church.</p>
               <p>Or, they were <hi>groſs, and leud Forgeries;</hi> compoſed by the Enemies of Chriſtians: with deſign only to make ſport with a Crew of Blockheads, that were always ready to ſwallow any thing; never ſo ſilly and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous; provided it were but miraculous, and had a few good Morals.</p>
               <p>Or, we owe them to a certain <hi>pious fraud,</hi> to which the Antients were much given; that ſought to magnify Chriſtianity, by theſe pompous Tales and Additions to it: the true Apoſtolic Writings being too imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, to raiſe in mens Minds any great appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>Yet leſt we ſhould not by all this fully un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them, they are mindful and <hi>careful</hi> to add, that; theſe Writings and Books how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever were quoted, and reverenced by many of the Antients or Fathers: and <hi>that,</hi> no more than this can be ſaid, on behalf of the Books (of our Canon) that are preſerved; and not ſo much, for divers of them. Or more in ſhort; the latter are not a ruſh better, or wiſer, than the former: ſaving only that, <hi>they have had the good luck to be preſerved,</hi> by Knaves; <hi>and magnified, by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:32695:18"/>Fools.</hi> Let us call over, and diſcuſs theſe things.</p>
               <p>The Books of the Catalogue were once in reputation, in ſome Places, and with divers Learned Perſons; but they are now partly loſt, partly very much ſuſpected as not Genuin.</p>
               <p>We anſwer; Seventeen hundred years, the undeniable ſufficiency of the Books which are preſerved, and <hi>that</hi> the Books of the Catalogue were not timely communicated to the principal Churches, are obvious and probable Reaſons, that ſo many of 'em have miſcarried, and the reſt are of doubtful Credit. Some People are pleaſed to laugh at this; and chooſe rather to gueſs, that, the Books we talk of, have been either ſuppreſt or ſlighted, becauſe they were not <hi>to the tooth of the ſtrongeſt ſide;</hi> or were the <hi>Mock compoſitions, of Enemies;</hi> or the <hi>Holy Cheats</hi> of Perſons that: ſought to aggrandize Chriſtianity. That is, without ever having ſeen theſe Books; without having heard of moſt of them, under any other Character by the Antients, than that <hi>they were known but to few:</hi> they pronounce over them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitly, or <hi>without diſtinguiſhing them;</hi> that, they were <hi>lend Cheats,</hi> or <hi>pious Fraeuds,</hi> or <hi>told ſome dangerous Tales</hi> that the political and prevailing Party thought fit to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:32695:19"/>
               <p>Who ſees not, theſe are Suppoſitions that a man may make at will, concerning any Books that are loſt; or any ſuch Books, that the Evidences of their being Genuin and ſound, have miſcarried? but they are <hi>mere</hi> Conjectures? and ſuch as neither Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, nor Prudence, ſuffers us to make, when we have others that are extremely <hi>probable,</hi> and ſome of them <hi>certain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I gave ſome Inſtances before of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical, Hiſtorical, and Philoſophical Books; that are loſt: there is no learned Man that would approve of ſuch a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as this, concerning them; they have periſht becauſe <hi>they were Trifles,</hi> or <hi>Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> or ſhot ſome <hi>ſuch Bolts, as the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of wiſer men could not away with.</hi> I leave the matter with the indifferent, to judg of it; as their Wit, and Honeſty, ſhall diſpoſe 'em.</p>
               <p>I added, at our entrance into this Diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; <q>Nothing can be objected to the Catalogue, but what one would look for: <hi>that,</hi> in ſo various a Subject, ſome more Books are written, than the <hi>ſevere</hi> ſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny of the Catholic Church would (ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely) approve; and <hi>that,</hi> ſome Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flers and Impoſtors would <hi>perhaps</hi> be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing their ſhameful Talents, among the honeſt and well-qualified.</q> I meant hereby, if we grant that moſt or almoſt all
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32695:19"/>(or if you will, <hi>all</hi>) the Books of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue were Spurious; that they were pious Frauds, or impious Cheats, or have been ſuppreſt by the Jealouſy of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing ſide: it will not in the leaſt affect the Scripture-Canon, or Chriſtian Religion; which are not the leſs true, or leſs certain, becauſe there have been ſome falſe Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and falſe Pretenders to Revelation. Infidelity and Profanity are hard put to it, when their whole ſtrength is reduced to this: there have been ſome <hi>falſe</hi> Evangeliſts, <hi>feigned</hi> Acts, Epiſtles, Revelations; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have no certainty of any true Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, Revelations, Epiſtles or Acts. As if they had ſaid; <hi>Lucius, Ambroſe,</hi> and <hi>Arthur,</hi> were <hi>fabulous</hi> Kings of <hi>Britain;</hi> and <hi>Jeffry</hi> of <hi>Monmouth</hi> has contrived a Britiſh Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, conſiſting chiefly of Tales of his own deviſing: therefore neither can we prove <hi>Caſſibelan, Caractacus,</hi> and <hi>Arviragus,</hi> were ſometimes Kings in this Iſland. Or if you will, thus; <hi>Iſidore Mercator</hi> publiſhed a Volume of <hi>Spurious</hi> Epiſtles of Popes and Biſhops, and Decrees of Councils: <hi>Annius</hi> of <hi>Viterbium</hi> ſomewhile deceived every body, with a <hi>Counterfeit Metaſthenes,</hi> a <hi>Beroſus Manetho</hi> and <hi>Philo.</hi> Therefore, we ought not to think, there were at all any ſuch Councils, Biſhops, and Popes; or a <hi>real Metaſthenes, a Beroſus, Philo,</hi> and <hi>Manetho,</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:32695:20"/>who were Learned and celebrated Writers and Hiſtorians. Why don't they alledg the <hi>Alchoran</hi> too, as an Exception, and Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Scripture Canon; and ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one was an Impoſture, ſo muſt the other?</p>
               <p>Our Author ſeems to be aware, of ſome ſuch Exceptions as theſe; and therefore makes ſhort work with us, by intimating (in a great many places) that; <q>
                     <hi>The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are the ſame,</hi> why we ſhould reject, or receive the Catalogue, and (preſent) Scripture-Canon: as much may be ſaid <hi>for,</hi> or <hi>againſt</hi> one, as the other.</q> We will examine this; and the Pretences, with which 'tis ſupported, very carefully.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:32695:20"/>
               <head>Of the Verity, and Certainty of the Scripture-Canon.</head>
               <p>I Shall reduce into the beſt Method, and moſt natural Order that I can, what is any way conſiderable in our Author's Book; concerning the Scripture-Canon: diſcuſſing every particular, as I recite or mention it.</p>
               <p>From P. 69, to P. 79; he has a Quota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of <hi>M. Dodwel,</hi> to this ſenſe. <q>The Books of the preſent Canon, lay conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Coffers of particular Churches, or of private Men; [the Churches and Men to whom they were written] till the latter times of <hi>Trajan,</hi> or rather of <hi>Adrian:</hi> [that is, till about 130 years after Chriſt.] We are not to think that; the Writers of the New Teſtament, knew any thing of the Goſpels, or other Books of the Canon, that were not wrote by themſelves; or <hi>that,</hi> the Clergy made a Common uſe, either of the one or other. We have ſtill ſome Eccleſiaſtical Writers, of thoſe early times; <hi>Clemens Romanus, Barnabas, Hermas, Ignatius,</hi> and <hi>Polycarp:</hi> but in <hi>Hermas,</hi> there is not one paſſage out of the New Teſtament;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32695:21"/>in the reſt, not any of the Evangeliſt is called by his Name, of is particularly named. Nor can we know, whether the Paſſages they cite, are alledged out of the Goſpels or other Books of our preſent Canon; or from other Goſpels and Books, namely the Books of the Catalogue: for the Citations are very different, from the Words in our preſent Goſpels and other Canonical Books; and for the moſt part have ſomething added to them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amyntor</hi> declares, he aſſents to all this; and farther to recommend it, he complements <hi>M. Dodwel</hi> after a very extraordinary man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. He affirms, <q>
                     <hi>M. Dodwel,</hi> tho a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, knows as much of theſe matters, as the Divines of all Churches put together.</q> What an advantage is it ſometimes to a man, not to be <hi>a thing in Holy Orders?</hi> how much more knowing, and Learned ſhall he be, than himſelf was aware: for I take it for granted, this Bounce of a Complement was wholly intended to <hi>M. Dodwel</hi>'s Lay-quality. I am content for my part, <hi>M. Dodwel</hi> be the next <hi>HERO,</hi> to <hi>M. Milton;</hi> I hope how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever 'twill be granted, that how much ſoever <hi>M. Dodwel</hi> knows, <hi>he does not know that to be true, which is falſe:</hi> and in confidence of this, I intend to diſcuſs, what he hath ſaid. Or rather, to ſpeak with due reſerve of a Perſon and Matter that I my ſelf do
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32695:21"/>not know, what <hi>Amyntor</hi> hath imputed to him.</p>
               <p>He ſays, <q>The Writers of the New Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament were unknown to one another; and to the Churches, and Clergy; till 130 years after Chriſt.</q> How do I fear, leſt he that is ſaid to know as much of theſe Matters, as the Clergy of all Churches put together, ſhould be found to know leſs of 'em; than any of us Country-Curats? For firſt, as to the Writers of the four <hi>Goſpels;</hi> all the Church-Hiſtorians agree, St. <hi>Matthew</hi> wrote firſt, ſo it will not be expected we ſhould prove, that he had ſeen the reſt: but 'tis apparent, the next Evangeliſt, <hi>Mark,</hi> had ſeen and read the Goſpel by St. <hi>Matthew;</hi> becauſe <hi>Mark</hi>'s Goſpel is indeed nothing elſe but an abridgment of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s, as the Critics and Interpreters have (many of them) obſerved. They are the words of <hi>H. Grotius,</hi> on <hi>Mark</hi> 1.1. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſum eſſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Matthaei Evangelio, apertum facit colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio:</hi> i. e. If we compare their Goſpels, it will be evident that St. <hi>Mark</hi> made great uſe of the Goſpel by <hi>Matthew.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin, de Conſ. Eccl.</hi> c. 2. ſays: <hi>Marcus Matthaeum ſubſecutus; tanquam pediſſequus, &amp; breviator ejus videtur.</hi> i. e. As St. <hi>Mark</hi> wrote <hi>in time</hi> after St. <hi>Matthew;</hi> ſo he follows him as it were at the very heels, <hi>in reſpect of the things related,</hi> only abridging what St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> had more largely ſaid.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:32695:22"/>
               <p>After <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark,</hi> came St. <hi>Luke;</hi> he is very reaſonably and probably thought to intend (beſides we know not who elſe) <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark;</hi> in thoſe firſt words of his Goſpel. <q>For as much as MANY have taken in hand, to ſet forth in order a Declaration of thoſe things, which are ſurely believed among us; even as they delivered them to us, who <hi>from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning</hi> were <hi>Eye-witneſſes,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters of the Word:</hi> it ſeemed good to me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Thoſe Characters of <hi>Eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> and <hi>from the beginning,</hi> and <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Word,</hi> agree to the Perſon of St. <hi>Matthew;</hi> and the two laſt to St. <hi>Mark:</hi> that to ſay the whole Period was intended of <hi>them,</hi> at leaſt <hi>with others,</hi> is what has been reaſonably believed hitherto; and is not made leſs reaſonable by the two Exceptions by <hi>Amyntor,</hi> taken (as he ſaith) out of <hi>M. Dodwel.</hi> They alledg, that; St. <hi>Luke</hi> has given a <hi>different Genealogy</hi> of our Saviour, from that by St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> without giving <hi>any reaſon</hi> for it: and that, there are many <hi>apparent Contradictions,</hi> between theſe (and other) Writers of Scripture. But if theſe Gentlemen pleaſe to look into <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.6. and <hi>Luke</hi> 3.31. they will ſee <hi>a reaſon</hi> of the difference of the Genealogies: namely that, St. <hi>Matthew</hi> deduces the Genealogy from <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> from <hi>Nathan;</hi> both of them
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:32695:22"/>Sons of <hi>David,</hi> and Anceſtors to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>in the ſenſe that</hi> David <hi>was his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor.</hi> As for the <hi>apparent Contradictions,</hi> between theſe Evangeliſts; if it were true, it would rather prove that St. <hi>Luke</hi> had ſeen and read thoſe other two Evangeliſts: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by writing any thing contrary to them, he intended without doubt to correct their Miſtake; and rightly inform their common Readers. But 'tis certain he was not in the leaſt aware, that thoſe former Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts needed any correction; for himſelf, we have ſeen before, bears 'em witneſs, that they had written all things <hi>as thoſe Perſons have alſo deliver'd them to us, who from the beginning were Eye-witneſſes, and Miniſters of the WORD:</hi> that is, as the other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and firſt Preachers, have alſo dediver'd them, by word of mouth.</p>
               <p>The laſt Evangeliſt was St. <hi>John;</hi> how he came to be an Evangeliſt, or on what occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he wrote, <hi>Euſebius</hi> (the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edeſt Hiſtorian</hi> of the Church) will tell us, in theſe words: <q>The Goſpels of <hi>Matthew, Mark,</hi> and <hi>Luke, being in all mens hands, came alſo to the knowledg of the Apoſtle</hi> John; who approved them, as faithfully written. But he obſerved, they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in this reſpect, that; they had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that part of our Saviour's Actions and Preaching, which preceded the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:32695:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>John the Baptiſt:</hi> for they all begin their Narratives, with the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment of <hi>John.</hi> — Hereupon, St. <hi>John</hi> being thereto requeſted, added (in a Goſpel by him) the Time and Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that had been omitted by the other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts. <bibl>
                        <hi>Euſeb.</hi> H. E. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul</hi> are another conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of the Canon of the New Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament; our Oppoſers ſay, <q>They lay hid in the coffers of the Churches and Perſons to whom they were written, till 130 years after Chriſt.</q> I ask, How then came St. <hi>Peter</hi> to ſay, <q>
                     <bibl>2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</bibl> As our beloved Brother <hi>Paul,</hi> according to the Wiſdom given to him, hath written to you; <hi>as alſo in all his Epiſtles,</hi> ſpeaking (to them) of theſe things: in which (E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles) are ſome things, hard to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; which they that are unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and unſtable do wreſt (as they do alſo the other Scriptures) to their own Damnation.</q> This Teſtimony proves, not <add>only</add> that St. <hi>Peter</hi> had ſeen the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul;</hi> but that <hi>they were commonly read,</hi> and a very bad Uſe made of 'em by ſome.</p>
               <p>The remaining part of the Canon, even the Catholic or General Epiſtles, by St. <hi>James,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> St. <hi>Jude;</hi> and the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> becauſe they were written ſome of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:32695:23"/>them to <hi>whole Nations,</hi> and the reſt to <hi>all Chriſtians,</hi> not to particular Perſons or Churches; we muſt needs underſtand they <hi>were publiſhed,</hi> by thoſe Apoſtles themſelves. They could be no otherwiſe written and addreſſed to Nations, and to <hi>all</hi> Chriſtians; but by ſuch a general Publication, as when we now give a Copy of a Letter or Book, to a Bookſeller, to be by him made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
               <p>It appears (I ſuppoſe) by all this, to indifferent Perſons, that; 'tis utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, that the Writers of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were ſtrangers to the Writings of one another; is it any better, what follows next? namely that:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Neither did the Clergy, or Churches, know of the Goſpels; and other Books, of our preſent Canon. We have ſtill, <hi>ſay theſe Gentlemen,</hi> ſome Eccleſiaſtical Writers of thoſe early times; <hi>Clemens Romanus, Barnabas, Hermas, Ignatius,</hi> and <hi>Polycarp.</hi> Of theſe, <hi>Hermas</hi> has not one paſſage out of all the New Teſtament: and for the places that are cited by the reſt, <hi>one cannot tell</hi> whether they are taken out of the Books of the preſent Canon; or out of the Spurious Books, [even thoſe of the Catalogue, or ſome ſuch.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hermas</hi> has not one paſſage <hi>out of the New Teſtament.</hi> Therefore, what? Why,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32695:24"/>therefore as we were ſaying, and are now proving; <hi>Hermas</hi> had not read the Books of the New Teſtament, which were all ſtill (and long after, even to the year 130) in the Coffers of Perſons and Churches to whom they were writen. And I ſay, <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> has not cited a word <hi>out of the whole Old Teſtament.</hi> Had he not therefore read any of the Books, of that Teſtament? had not a profeſt Chriſtian, and a Writer (think they) read any Book of the Old or New Teſtament? It is apparent, he had read both: by the Doctrine of his Book; by his Diſcourſes on Baptiſm, Repentance, and all Chriſtian Virtues; by his Viſions, Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and Commands, of all which he had his Hints from the Books of Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, eſpecially the Prophetical. He even ſometimes expreſſes himſelf in the very words of the New Teſtament; as when he ſays, <hi>Com.</hi> 4. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. <hi>He that putteth away his wife, and marrieth another, committeth Adultery.</hi> Which he took, no doubt, from Sr. <hi>Luke;</hi> who uſes thoſe very words, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> manifeſtly alludes, to divers Expreſſions and Paſſages of the New Teſtament; and ſome he <hi>expreſly</hi> repeats, as <hi>Charity covereth a multitude of Sins;</hi> 1 Pet. 4.8. <hi>We are Members one of another,</hi> Rom. 12.5. <hi>He</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>is ſo much greater than
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32695:24"/>Angels; as he hath by inheritance obtained a more excellent Name, than they.</hi> Heb. 1.2, 4. <hi>Forgive, and ye ſhall be forgiven; — with what meaſure ye meet, it ſhall be meaſured to you again.</hi> Luke 6.37. <hi>Wo unto him by whom Offences come: It were better for him, that a Milſtone were hanged about his neck, and that he were caſt into the Sea; than that he ſhould offend one of my little ones.</hi> Luke 17.1, 2.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Polycarp</hi> takes notice, of the Epiſtle written by Sr. <hi>Paul,</hi> to the <hi>Philippians;</hi> and ſaith, that Apoſtle mentions the <hi>Philippians</hi> with much Honor, in the beginning of his Epiſtle to them. So indeed he dos; calling them, <hi>the Saints at</hi> Philippi; and profeſſing that, <hi>upon every remembrance of them, by giveth thanks to God.</hi> Phil. 1.1, 2. He cites alſo the words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; as, <hi>Do ye not know that the Saints ſhall judg the World?</hi> 1 Cor. 6.2. <hi>Neither For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators, nor Effeminate, nor abuſers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with mankind, ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9, 10. <hi>We brought nothing into this World, and we can carry nothing out of it.</hi> 1 Tim. 6.7. He <hi>often</hi> repeats the Words and Expreſſions of St. <hi>Peter. Whom not having ſeen, ye love; in whom, tho now ye ſee him not, ye rejoice, with joy unſpeakable end full of Glory.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 1.8. <hi>Who his own ſelf hare our Sins, in his own Body, on the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:32695:25"/>Tree: — who did no Sin; nor was Guile found in his Mouth.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.22, 24. <hi>Having your Converſation, honeſt among the Gentiles.</hi> Out of St. <hi>John,</hi> he hath; <hi>Whoſoever doth not confeſs, that; Jeſus Chriſt is come in the Fleſh; this is Anti-Chriſt.</hi> 1 John. 4.3. From the Evangeliſts <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Luke,</hi> he gives us theſe Paſſages. <hi>Bleſſed are they, that are perſecuted for Righteouſneſs ſake; for theirs is the Kingdom of God.</hi> Matth. 5.10. <hi>Bleſſed are the Poor, for theirs is the Kingdom of God.</hi> Luke 6.10. <hi>The Spirit truly is willing, but the Fleſh is weak.</hi> Matth. 26.41.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clemens</hi> and <hi>Polycarp</hi> affect to ſpeak, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they have to ſay, in the words of Scripture; eſpecially of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> rather uſes his own way of Expreſſion, but he ſaith from St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew; He that is able to receive this, let him receive it.</hi> Matth. 19.12. <hi>The Tree is known, by his Fruit.</hi> Matth. 12.33. From St. <hi>Paul</hi> he borrows, <hi>who hath given himſelf for us, an Offering and Sacrifice, to God.</hi> Eph. 5.2. <hi>Be perfectly joined together, in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment; and all ſpeak the ſame things.</hi> 1 Cor. 1.10. <hi>Where is the Wiſe, where is the Diſputer?</hi> 1 Cor. 1.23.</p>
               <p>They have but one Witneſs more, to call, St. <hi>Barnabas;</hi> who alſo is againſt them, not much leſs than the former: for he alledges
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32695:25"/>from St. <hi>Matthew, Many are called, but few are choſen.</hi> Matth. 20.16. and 22.14. <hi>He came not to call the Righteous, but Sinners to repentance.</hi> Matth. 9.13. In his 19th Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he giveth an Abſtract or Summary of the Moral and Practical Duties of Chriſtianity, or <hi>the way of Life</hi> as he ſpeaks: it appears, both by the matter and manner of ſpeaking, <hi>He meant to abridg the morality, of the Old, and New Teſtaments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we now conſider that, theſe Pieces are only Epiſtles, or Letters; and ſome of them ſo brief, that they may be written on a ſheet of Paper: we may rather wonder, that theſe Fathers have quoted ſo much Scripture; than that we meet ſo little in their Letters. And when <hi>M. Dodwel</hi> and <hi>Amyntor</hi> ſay, <hi>They cannot tell, whether theſe Citations are from the Books of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, or from ſome of the Apocryphal Books of the Catalogue;</hi> they put me hard to it, to imagine <hi>what they can tell:</hi> for they are the very words, neither more nor fewer, of the Canonical Books; and are extant in no other Writers, that I, or that they know; unleſs they ſhould be in the invalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (loſt) Decads of <hi>Titus Livius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to other Quotations out of theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that might alſo have been obſerved; in which, in repeating the words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they ſometimes ſubſtitute an equivalent
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:32695:26"/>word (or words) for the word in the Scripture-Text: it was not, becauſe they were quoting ſome Apocryphal Goſpel, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, or Acts; but becauſe <hi>they cited by memory.</hi> Wanting Concordances, and our other Modern Helps; they could not, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much trouble to themſelves, be always exact in repeating Scripture-Texts as to the <hi>words,</hi> tho they keep well enough to the <hi>ſenſe.</hi> And for this reaſon alſo, they do not always name the Scripture-Author whom they alledg; even to avoid the (poſſible) Miſtake of one Writer for another.</p>
               <p>I make but this one remark more, on the Citations of Scripture, by theſe Fathers. It is reckned, they all wrote before the whole Canon of the New Teſtament was compleated; <hi>M. Dodwel</hi> ſays expreſly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Jude</hi> or the two <hi>Johns</hi> had written. And they wrote from places, very diſtant from <hi>Judea,</hi> and from one another; <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> and <hi>Clemens</hi> from <hi>Rome, Barnabas</hi> from <hi>Cyprus; Polycarp Smyrna</hi> in <hi>Aſia, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> from <hi>Syria.</hi> This ſerves to aſſure us that, the Goſpels and Apoſtolic Writings were immediately communicated; either by particular care of the Churches, or (more probably) a publication; to <hi>the moſt remote</hi> Biſhops and Churches: that there can be nothing more contrary to Truth, and to the zeal and Diligence of the firſt Chriſtians
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32695:26"/>and Churches, than this Affirmation of <hi>M. Dodwel,</hi> and his Second; that the Apoſtolic Writings were lockt up in Coffers, of the Churches and Perſons to whom they were written, till 130 years after Chriſt. Which is ſo far, we have ſeen, from being true; that all the Writers of thoſe times, tho living in places <hi>ſome Thouſands of miles diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant from one another, and from Judea,</hi> adorn even their familiar Letters, with Flowers from the four Goſpels, and Epiſtles of the preſent Canon: nor do they cite, that we know of, a ſingle Sentence from the Books of the Catalogue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amyntor</hi> however, tho he aſſents to <hi>M. Dodwel,</hi> in ſaying that, our preſent Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Canon, and the Books that compoſe it, were unknown to the Churches and Clergy, till 130 years after Chriſt: yet he doth not think, <hi>Barnabas, Hermas, Clemens, Polycarp,</hi> or <hi>Ignatius,</hi> were the real Authors of thoſe Epiſtles that go under their Names; but that theſe Epiſtles were forged about ſuch time, as ſo many other Impoſtures ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the Catholic Church, namely a good while after the year 130. But here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, he hath entirely given up the Cauſe he was maintaining. <hi>M. Dodwel</hi> ſpeaks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtently to himſelf, tho not truly; when he ſays, the Scripture-Canon was not known to the Churches or Clergy till about the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:32695:27"/>year 130, becauſe <hi>Clemens</hi> (and the other Writers of thoſe times) cite nothing out of the ſaid Canon. But <hi>Amyntor</hi> forgets to be conſiſtent to his Cauſe, when he ſays, the Canonical Books were not known till the year 130; and at the ſame time denies, we have any Monuments left of thoſe anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times, <hi>Clemens</hi> and the reſt being of much later date, and alſo Impoſtures.</p>
               <p>Beſides, granting to him, that theſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles are Impoſtures; deviled more than 130 years after Chriſt, as 150 or 180 after our Saviour: yet having quoted abundance of Paragraphs out of our preſent Canon, and <hi>none out of the Books of the Catalogue;</hi> as we are hereby aſſured, that the former were <hi>then</hi> known, and approved as Books of <hi>received and allowed</hi> Authority, ſo <q>the other either were not known, or not conſider'd as Books whoſe Authority <hi>could oblige, or ſo much as perſuade.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>There were divers <hi>other</hi> Writers of thoſe early times, beſides <hi>Clemens</hi> and the reſt mentioned by <hi>M. Dodwel;</hi> and tho their Works are loſt, yet we have certain aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that they quoted the Books of the New Teſtament. <hi>Papias,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hiera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis,</hi> was Scholar of St. <hi>John,</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of <hi>Polycarp; Euſebius</hi> had read his Works, and takes (occaſional) notice that <hi>he quotes the Epiſtles of St.</hi> John, <hi>and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:32695:27"/>St.</hi> Peter. <hi>Euſeb. H. E. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap. ult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Contemporaries to <hi>Papias</hi> and <hi>Polycarp,</hi> and much within the term of 130 after Chriſt, was <hi>Quadratus, Agrippa</hi> ſirnamed <hi>Caſtor,</hi> and <hi>Baſilides.</hi> Of theſe, <hi>Baſilides</hi> wrote 24 Books of Commentaries (or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planations) on the Goſpels. Concerning the other two, <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith, <q>They, with <hi>many more,</hi> made it their buſineſs, to preach in places, whereas yet Churches were not gathered; and (τῶν θείων Ἐυανγε<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>λίων παραδιδόναι γραφὴν) <hi>to beſtow and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe Copies of the Inſpired Goſpels.</hi> 
                     <bibl>H. E. Lib. 3. c. 37. Lib. 4. c. 7.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in his Second Apology, but 140 years after Chriſt, (as Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> hath proved;) makes us to know that, there was then a particular Officer in the Churches, called <hi>the Reader,</hi> diſtinct from the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; whoſe buſineſs it was, ſaith he, <hi>to read the Prophetical and Apoſtolical Books to the Congregation, until it is ſufficient. Amyntor</hi> muſt ſuppoſe with great liberty, if he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, that in the year 130 the Books of the New Teſtament were unknown to the Churches and Clergy; and that, but ten years after, they were ſo known, and in ſuch credit, that the Churches entertained an Officer on purpoſe to read them, in their Aſſemblies.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:32695:28"/>
               <p>But why do we protract a Diſpute; and ſeek to old Authors known to few People, to determine it; when it may be ended by one (demonſtrative) Argument, and of which all Perſons are capable? <q>The four Goſpels, Acts, general Epiſtles, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, were not written to particular Perſons, or particular Churches; but written, and publiſhed to all the World. Let me hear <hi>Amyntor,</hi> or <hi>M. Dodwel,</hi> ſay; they were not <hi>written to be publiſhed,</hi> or were not <hi>publiſhed ſo ſoon as written:</hi> if they dare not ſay ſo; why do they ſay, they were kept in private Coffers, till 130 years after Chriſt? I don't think, any body will believe; that, the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or Clergy <hi>were ignorant of the publiſhst Books of their Religion.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:32695:28"/>
               <head>A Continuation of the Defence of the Canon.</head>
               <p>ANother Detraction of our Author, from the Credibility and juſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Canon, is that; <q>The prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Fathers of the three firſt Ages, <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus, Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> and <hi>Origen,</hi> did quote divers Books of the Catalogue (particularly <hi>Barnabas, Hermas, Ignatius, Polycarp,</hi> and <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi>) <hi>as Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> And why ſhould not all the Books that are cited by theſe Learned Fathers, <hi>as Scripture,</hi> be accounted <hi>equally</hi> Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic and Canonical? Or if theſe Diſciples and Succeſſors of the Apoſtles, could ſo groſly confound the genuin Writings of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles, with ſuch as are ſpurious and falſly attributed to them; how came others [the following Fathers, and the Councils, who have undertaken to declare which Books are Canonical, and which not,] to be better or more certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed? In ſhort, he ſaith; <hi>Clemens Romanus, Barnabas, Ignatius, Hermas,</hi> and <hi>Polycarp,</hi> were eſteemed by the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents to be <hi>as good as any part of the New Testament:</hi> and ſeeing herein they were
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32695:29"/>ſo groſly miſtaken; what ſtreſs can be laid on their Teſtimony, concerning the Books of the New Teſtament itſelf? which Teſtimony however, both formerly and at preſent, is alledged as the <hi>principal rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> (ſometimes he maketh it to be the <hi>only-reaſon,</hi>) why the Books of the New Teſtament are received as Canonical. <hi>Amynt.</hi> p. 44, 45, 46, 52, 79, 80. He adds, at <hi>p.</hi> 57, 58. The Council of <hi>Laodicea, An.</hi> 360 after Chriſt, is <hi>the firſt Aſſembly</hi> wherein the Canon of Scripture was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined. In ſo great a variety of Books (thoſe of the Catalogue, <hi>he means,</hi> and thoſe of the Canon;) how could that Council determine, which were the true Writings of the Apoſtles, and which not; but <hi>by Revelation,</hi> or the written <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Predeceſſors?</hi> Revelation in the caſe there was none: and for Teſtimony, I have the ſame Teſtimony for the Books I defend, which is uſually urged in behalf of <hi>the Canon.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>We may abridg, and diſtinguiſh this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, into theſe Propoſitions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>beſt</hi> of the Antients eſteemed the Writings that now go under the names of <hi>Clemens Romanus, Hermas, Barnabas, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> and <hi>Polycarp,</hi> to be as good Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as any part of the New Teſtament was then, or is now, accounted.</item>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:32695:29"/>
                  <item>2. The true Canon can be aſcertained, only by Revelation, or the Teſtimony of the Fathers: Revelation there was none; and the Teſtimony of the Fathers is as home and full for <hi>Clemens, Ignatius,</hi> and the reſt, not to mention many other Books of the Catalogue, as for our Canonical Books.</item>
                  <item>3. 'Tis even certain that, the Fathers were miſtaken in the Opinion they had concerning (the pretended) <hi>Clemens, Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Barnabas, Polycarp,</hi> and <hi>Ignatius;</hi> therefore, neither is their Teſtimony va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable concerning the Books of the New Teſtament, or preſent Scripture Canon.</item>
               </list>
               <p>We ſhall anſwer ſufficiently, if we prove clearly and indubitably theſe two things; <hi>That</hi> the Antients had not the ſame, or <hi>like</hi> regard for <hi>Clemens Romanus, Barnabas,</hi> or any other Books of the Catalogue, as for the Books of the Canon: and <hi>that,</hi> they had other (and <hi>ſtronger</hi>) reaſons, beſides <hi>the Teſtimony of their Predeceſſors,</hi> why they eſtabliſh'd the preſent Canon; or in other words, why they received the Books of the Canon, and not thoſe of the Catalogue.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Amyntor</hi> ſays, the <hi>beſt</hi> of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Antients quote the Writings of <hi>Barnabas, Hermas, Clemens Romanus, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> and <hi>Polycarp; as Canonical, and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> and <hi>that,</hi> they eſteemed them <hi>as
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:32695:30"/>good as any part of the New Teſtament.</hi> For this <hi>latter</hi> he will never be able to produce one Teſtimony of any of the Antients; and I ſhall abundantly prove the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, from thoſe Fathers to whom he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals, and whoſe ſenſe he hath ſo much miſtaken: for the <hi>other,</hi> were it true, yet 'tis not to the purpoſe. For 'tis certain, and granted by all Learned Men, that; thoſe Fathers called all the Antient Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Books, if they were Orthodox, <hi>Scripture,</hi> and <hi>Canonical:</hi> the terms <hi>Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> and <hi>Scripture</hi> were not then appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, to <hi>Books written by Inſpiration;</hi> but were common to <hi>all Eccleſiaſtical Writers and Books,</hi> if Orthodox. <hi>Origen,</hi> for inſtance, often cites the <hi>Apocryphal Books</hi> of the Old Teſtament, as Scripture, and Canonical; in his Homilies, and ſometimes when he is diſputing: but when he diſcourſes <hi>profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly,</hi> what Books are <hi>Divine Scripture,</hi> and what are not; he admits only thoſe Books of the Old Teſtament that are received by Proteſtants, rejecting the Apocryphal Books; ſee concerning this <hi>Euſeb.</hi> H. E. <hi>l.</hi> 6. c. 25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clemens Romanus, Hermas,</hi> and divers more, are cited <hi>as Scripture</hi> by the Antients and Fathers; ſays <hi>Amyntor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which of 'em? He anſwers; by <hi>Irenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> and <hi>Origen:</hi> and he refers us to places in their Writings. But
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:32695:30"/>in ſome of thoſe places, nothing at all is ſaid by thoſe Fathers, concerning the Books of which we are inquiring; in other places, the Authors are named, but nothing is quoted out of them: elſewhere are Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions out of them, but not under the names of Scripture or Canonical; and where they are ſo called, 'tis only in the ſenſe that the ſame (and many later) Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers call the <hi>Apocryphal Books of the Old Teſtament,</hi> Canonical or Scripture, and yet deny them to be of <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> or to be received by the Churches as <hi>a Rule of their Faith.</hi> Yet more particularly,</p>
               <p>It is not true that <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> in the alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed place or elſewhere, calls the Epiſtle of <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> Scripture. He cites it, only to prove that, <q>
                     <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition</hi> is contrary to the Hereſy which teaches, <hi>there is a God above the Creator of the World:</hi> becauſe, ſaith he, the ſaid Epiſtle of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> which is <hi>older</hi> than that deteſtable and fooliſh Hereſy, teaches <hi>but one God, All-mighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth.</hi>
                  </q> In the ſame Book and Chapter (<hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3.) he commends the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of <hi>Polycarp,</hi> but cites nothing out of, or calls it Scripture and Canonical. That, <hi>Hermas</hi> is mentioned by <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> I don't remember: <hi>Amyntor</hi> refers to <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. but nothing is there ſaid of him. As
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:32695:31"/>to <hi>Ignatius, Irenaeus</hi> only calls him, <hi>Quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ex Noſtris adjudicatum ad Beſtias prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Deum,</hi>
                  <q>One of us Chriſtians condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Beaſts for the cauſe of God.</q> He doth not ſo much as name him; but 'tis gueſſed he means <hi>Ignatius,</hi> becauſe the words he quotes are found in an Epiſtle of <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis no wonder that, <hi>Clemens Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> may call the Epiſtle of <hi>Barnabas</hi> and the Paſtor of <hi>Hermas,</hi> Scripture; in the ſenſe before mentioned: as <hi>a term of diſtinction,</hi> or to diſtinguiſh them from the Writings of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Moraliſts and Philoſophers, whom alſo he often cites, and explains their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. <hi>Euſebius</hi> (H. E. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 13.) obſerves that, <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> quotes the <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> or the Wiſdom of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Son of <hi>Syrac;</hi> and with them, the Epiſtles of <hi>Barnabas, Clemens Romanus,</hi> and others not univerſally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived among Chriſtians. Now as <hi>the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Solomon</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> were never reckoned by the Catholic Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (undoubtedly) neither by <hi>Clemens,</hi> as <hi>parts</hi> of the Old Teſtament, but only as laudable Appendices to it: ſo when we find him quoting alſo <hi>Hermas, Barnabas,</hi> or <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> under the ſame names and Epithets that he gives to <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> and (the falſe) <hi>Solomon;</hi> he intended no
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32695:31"/>more thereby to make them parts of the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament, than he (or the Catholick Church) accounted the other to be parts of the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament.</p>
               <p>What I ſay, is yet more plain from <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> the laſt of <hi>Amyntor</hi>'s Fathers. All the Apocryphal Books of the Old Teſtament, are frequently alledged by <hi>Origen;</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with his Citations out of the genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine Books of the New and Old Teſtaments: he has cauſed us however to know the vaſt difference, he put between them; and that the Catholick Church received only the preſent (Proteſtant) Canon, as <hi>Divine Scripture,</hi> the other Books (whether the Apocryphal Books of <hi>the Old Teſtament,</hi> or thoſe of <hi>the Catalogue,</hi>) only as uſeful and commendable Writings. He tells us, as to the Canon of the New Teſtament; <q>There are <hi>only four Goſpels:</hi> the firſt by <hi>Matthew,</hi> written for the uſe of the Jews; the next by <hi>Mark,</hi> who had his Information by St. <hi>Peter;</hi> the Goſpel by <hi>Luke,</hi> intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> laſtly, <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel. Concerning the Writings of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> he mentions only his Epiſtles: they are ſhort, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> and not to all the Churches which he had planted, or where he had taught. Peter, <hi>ſo he goes on,</hi> wrote an Epiſtle that is received and eſteemed by all; we may grant he wrote a ſecond Epiſtle, but
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:32695:32"/>it is doubted of. <hi>John</hi> wrote a Goſpel, and Revelation; a ſhort Epiſtle: and if you will, a ſecond, and third Epiſtle; but the two laſt are alſo queſtioned by ſome. He thinks thoſe Churches are to be commended, that receive <hi>the Epiſtle to the Hebrews;</hi> for our Anceſtors reckon it to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and had doubtleſs good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why they did ſo. <bibl>
                        <hi>Origen, Expoſ. in Joan.</hi> l. 5. <hi>&amp; in Matth.</hi> l. 1. <hi>Euſeb.</hi> H. E. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</bibl>
                  </q> We ſee then, in reckoning up the genuin Works of the Apoſtles, and Books that they thought to be <hi>Divine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Origen</hi> does not vouchſafe ſo much as to mention any of the Books of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue: he knows nothing of other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels, Acts, Revelations, or Epiſtles, beſides thoſe of our preſent Canon. Not that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he did not well know them, and alſo eſteem ſome of them; for he frequently quotes them both in Preaching and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but when he profeſſes to declare the true <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Canon,</hi> and genuin Works of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles; he forgets all the Books of the Catalogue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amyntor</hi> is very earneſt for <hi>the Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>the Revelation of St.</hi> Peter; on the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that they were approved, <hi>he ſaith,</hi> by the Antients, in particular by <hi>Origen: he ſaith,</hi> they may be preferred on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count before <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Epiſtle to the Hebrews,</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:32695:32"/>and other Books of our preſent Canon; which were doubted of, by the Antients. We have juſt now heard <hi>Origen</hi> ſay the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect contrary: we have ſeen, he and thoſe other Fathers make ſome doubt of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> the 2d of <hi>Peter,</hi> the 2d and 3d of <hi>John;</hi> but they ſpeak very favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably and very reſpectfully of them, and ſo as plainly to intimate that they incline to them: but the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> and other Books of the Catalogue, they never once name 'em, in recounting the Books of the Canon, or of the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts and Apoſtles. The teſtimony of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> in the caſe is ſo much the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, becauſe he was undoubtedly the moſt learned of all the Antients; the firſt Divine the Church ever had, ſome doubt not to add <hi>and the laſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Antagoniſt has not yet done with us, he ſays; <q>The Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 360 Years after Chriſt, is the <hi>firſt Aſſembly wherein the preſent Canon of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was eſtabliſh'd.</hi> In ſo great a variety of Books, (thoſe of the Catalogue, and thoſe of the Canon) how could that Council determine which were the true Writings of the Apoſtles, and which not; but by Revelation, or the written Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their Predeceſſors? Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Caſe there was none; and for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:32695:33"/>Teſtimony, I have the ſame Teſtimony for many Books of the Catalogue. Elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where (<hi>p.</hi> 48.) he adds; Divers Books of the Catalogue were verily ſuppoſed by the Antients, to be written by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, Apoſtles, and their Synergiſts whoſe name they bear: why then do we not receive 'em into the Canon, ſince the Authors of 'em were (at leaſt) Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions and Fellow-laborers of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles; as well as St. <hi>Mark</hi> and St. <hi>Luke?</hi> Why are they excluded from the Canon, and thoſe Evangeliſts not exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? If this quality (to have been a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion and Synergiſt of the Apoſtles) was ſufficient to entitle <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> to Inſpiration; why ſhould it not do as much for <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Clemens Romanus?</hi> And if this be not all the reaſon; pray let us know the true one, for I never heard of any other.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He is entred, I confeſs, on the merits of the Cauſe. He ſaith; the Council of <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea,</hi> that eſtabliſh'd our preſent Canon, could no other ways diſtinguiſh the genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Writings of the Apoſtles from thoſe falſly imputed to 'em, but by the Teſtimony of their Predeceſſors: he hath the ſame Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony, for the Books of the Catalogue. He knows no other reaſon, why <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> are believed to write by Inſpiration,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:32695:33"/>but that they were Synergiſts and Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the Apoſtles. I anſwer,</p>
               <p>That, he hath the ſame Teſtimony for ſome Books of the Catalogue, as we for the Books of the Canon; he attempted to prove from <hi>Irenaeus, Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Origen,</hi> his only Witneſſes. But <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus,</hi> I have ſhown, barely names ſome of thoſe Books; and for others, he cites them <hi>only as good Witneſſes of the true Eccleſiaſtical Tradition,</hi> not as <hi>Divine Scripture. Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> and <hi>Origen,</hi> may ſometimes call them Scripture; in the ſenſe that they ſo call the Apocryphal Books of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they (with the Proteſtants) deny to be <hi>parts</hi> of that Teſtament: and in reciting the Books of the Canon, and Works of the Apoſtles, they wholly omit, and ſometimes expreſly cenſure theſe Books of the Catalogue.</p>
               <p>The Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> nor any other, ever pretended, <hi>to eſtabliſh the Canon of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> which is precedaneous to all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, and receives no Authority from them, but they from it. <hi>Amyntor</hi> ſhould have ſaid, the Council of <hi>Laodicea</hi> is the firſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly that, on occaſion of ſome ſpurious, and many doubtful Books, declared which were the Books that had been certainly left to the Church by the Apoſtles and other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous (firſt) Preachers.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:32695:34"/>
               <p>'Tis no more true, <hi>that; Mark</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> are ſuppoſed to write by Inſpiration, only becauſe they were Companions and Syner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſts of the Apoſtles: and <hi>that,</hi> the Council of <hi>Laodicea</hi> declared the Scripture-Canon, from only the Teſtimony of their Anceſtors or Predeceſſors: that is, of the preceding Fathers, ſuch as <hi>Irenaeus, Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> and <hi>Origen. Euſebius,</hi> a long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> informed every body of the (ſound) Reaſons, why the Catholic Church receives ſome Books as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Scripture, and others not: his words are theſe. <q>Many Books have been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Heretics, under the names of the Apoſtles; as the Goſpels of <hi>Peter, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Matthias,</hi> and others; the Acts of <hi>Andrew, John,</hi> and divers more. But firſt, <hi>they are not cited</hi> [he means, not as <hi>Divine Scripture;</hi> for that they are indeed quoted by <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> the learnedſt of the <hi>Antenicens,</hi> he tells us before and after;] <hi>by the Doctors of the Church.</hi> Secondly, their way of writing is wholly <hi>different from the Spirit, Genius, and Manner of the Apoſtles.</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Doctrine, Opinions, and <hi>other</hi> Matters, advanced in thoſe Books, are ſo contrary to Truth, and to Orthodoxy; that we muſt not barely call them Spuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but Abſurd, and Impious. <bibl>
                        <hi>Euſeb.</hi> H. E. l. 3. c. 25.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:32695:34"/>
               <p>I muſt a little enlarge, on this important Teſtimony; which overthrows all <hi>Amyntor</hi>'s and <hi>M. Dodwel</hi>'s Pretences, either for the Books of the Catalogue, or againſt thoſe of the Canon.</p>
               <p>Theſe Books, ſaith <hi>Euſebius,</hi> are never cited <hi>(as Divine Scripture)</hi> by the Doctors of the Church: directly contrary to <hi>Amyntor</hi>'s <hi>I have the ſame Teſtimony of the Antients</hi> (the very beſt and ſoundeſt of them) for theſe Books, that is alledged (or can be) by others for the Canon.</p>
               <p>Theſe Writings, ſays <hi>Euſebius</hi> again, <hi>have nothing of the Apoſtolical Way and Spirit.</hi> They want that honeſt Plainneſs, in their Style; that Integrity of manners, that Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Piety, that Salt of Virtue, that exemption from Partialities and Paſſions; which ſo effectually recommend, and even point out to us, the Inſpired Writings.</p>
               <p>Above all, they are ſtuffed with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of notorious Falſities in Doctrine, and in Matters of Fact; and thoſe alſo <hi>as ridiculous,</hi> as they are erroneous.</p>
               <p>Here ſure we have, wherewith to anſwer, to all the bold Suggeſtions, of the Book under conſideration. If the Author pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, he has the ſame Teſtimony of ſome An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, for the Books of the Catalogue, as there is for the Canon: <hi>Euſebius</hi> replies, none of the Doctors have quoted thoſe Pieces, <hi>as
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:32695:35"/>Divine Scripture.</hi> If he demands, what <hi>other</hi> Exceptions we can advance againſt them; or what we can ſay <hi>farther,</hi> for the Books of the Canon: <hi>Euſebius</hi> again anſwers, the Books of the Canon and of the Catalogue differ, as Pious and Impious; as True and Falſe; as Credible and Ridiculous: and that theſe are the Churches Reaſons, why ſhe venerates the latter, and no leſs diſeſteems (to uſe no harder word) the other. In ſhort, beſides the unanimous Teſtimony of the Antients, which was <hi>Amyntor</hi>'s only Reaſon: <hi>Euſebius</hi> inſiſts, on the ſo <hi>different Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Morality,</hi> of theſe two ſorts of Books; and on the <hi>known</hi> Verity in Matters of Fact, and <hi>ſelf-evident</hi> ſoundneſs in Doctrine, ſo remarkably appearing in one, and wanting in the other. When <hi>Amyntor</hi> fairly ſatisfies theſe Anſwers, of this Learned Father; <hi>Phillida ſolus habeto.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:32695:35"/>
               <head>Farther Continuation of the Defence of the Canon.</head>
               <p>IT ſeems however, by all this we have gained nothing at all; for <hi>Amyntor</hi> ſays again. <q>If ſome of the Antients made theſe Exceptions, to the Books of the Catalogue; they were not ſo thought of, by ſome <hi>whole Parties,</hi> who made uſe of 'em. <hi>And,</hi> there is not a ſingle Book of the New Teſtament, which was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed by ſome of the Antients; as unjuſtly fathered on the Apoſtles, and really for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by their Enemies. And laſtly, he has Witneſſes for it, that; were the Books of the Canon never ſo certainly written by the Apoſtles: they have been however ſo changed, and that too divers times, that (perhaps) not a ſingle Rib or Plank of the old <hi>Argos</hi> is left.</q> To this effect he ſpeaks at <hi>p.</hi> 19, 56, 60, 64.</p>
               <p>But who told him, or how will he prove it, that; whereas ſome of the Ancients made Exceptions to the Books of the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, they were otherwiſe thought of, by ſome <hi>whole Parties</hi> of Chriſtians? It is not true, nor will he be able to bring any proof for it, from Antiquity; that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:32695:36"/>Acts, Epiſtles, Revelations, of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue, were eſpouſed by <hi>whole Parties</hi> or Sects. On the contrary, they were read indifferently by <hi>ſome</hi> of all Parties; they had a little while <hi>ſome</hi> Credit with ſome Perſons in all the Denominations of Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians: till for the Reaſons, but now alledged from <hi>Euſebius,</hi> they grew (firſt) into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe, and (then) were loſt. Or if ſome few of 'em were the Compoſitions of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Heretics, in order to countenance the Opinions of a ſmall Party; as the Goſpel of <hi>Judas Iſcariot,</hi> ſaid by <hi>Epiphanius</hi> to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by the <hi>Cainits,</hi> a Gnoſtic Sect: their manifeſt Diſagreement to <hi>the Doctrine</hi> and <hi>History</hi> of the Goſpels known by all to be Authentic, would (and actually did) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately detect, and juſtly diſcredit them. Some whole Parties, ſays <hi>Amyntor,</hi> eſpouſed ſome Books of the Catalogue. Yes, the <hi>Cainits;</hi> a Sect of two days continuance, and conſiſting (it may be) of twenty or thirty Perſons, <hi>Libertines;</hi> boaſted of the Goſpel of <hi>Judas.</hi> How does this weaken the Judgment, made of that Goſpel, by all the Churches, and reported by <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius;</hi> that this and ſome ſuch Pieces were fooliſh, and falſe, even to ridiculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? We don't deny, there were ſuch Books as theſe in the Catalogue; or <hi>that</hi> they were ſometime in ſuch credit, and even
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32695:36"/>favoured by particular Perſons of ſome Churches and Sects: but we ſay, the reaſons alledged againſt them by the body and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of the Churches, and that hereupon they ſoon became univerſally ſlighted, and ſhortly quite periſhed; are juſt ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions againſt them, as it will be in after-Ages againſt the (ſpurious) <hi>Metaſthenes, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſus,</hi> and <hi>Philo</hi> of <hi>Annius,</hi> that they had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared but a very little while, e're they were wholly diſcredited by the concurrent Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and clear Arguments of Learned Men. As no body hereafter will appear for <hi>Annius</hi> his <hi>Philo, Beroſus,</hi> or <hi>Metaſthenes:</hi> 'tis an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt not leſs worthy to be laught at, that the Goſpel of <hi>Judas</hi> has now any Fautors; or that any are found, who with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence do mind us, that, <hi>it was eſteemed ſome time by a Party.</hi> When the Judgment that Learned Men, and the Catholic Church, made of this Goſpel and other ſuch like Pieces, has been confirmed by the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate diſappearing of the Books and Parties that maintained them; what can we reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably think of the matter but that, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Orator has worded it for us, <hi>Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum portenta delet dies; Follies and Errors, that are too extravagant and monſtrous, ſoon (like the Monſters of Nature) periſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If there were any thing (indeed) that we could lay in the contrary Scale, had we
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32695:37"/>any thing to alledg in favor of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and loſt Books; it were a neceſſary Caution and Juſtice, not to condemn 'em merely on the account that the Fathers and firſt Churches cenſur'd and rejected 'em: but their Judgment, and Reaſons, againſt them; ſo approved by all, that the Books thereupon were all immediately <hi>put to ncceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary uſes;</hi> ought to ſatisfy us concerning them.</p>
               <p>To that; <q>There is not a ſingle Book of the New Teſtament, which was not refuſed by ſome of the Antients, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly father'd on the Apoſtles, and really forged by their Enemies; <bibl>
                        <hi>P.</hi> 56, 64.</bibl>
                  </q> Thought I, when I read it; has this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man found ſome of the firſt (loſt) Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians of the Church, pack'd up in a cloſe Cheſt, or Hogſhead, and buried ſo many Ages un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ground? Has he recovered <hi>Hegeſippus,</hi> or other Antient Writers; that are ſo much praiſed by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> St. <hi>Jerom, Photius;</hi> and other Fathers who were curious of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and have left ſome ſmall account of thoſe loſt Treaſures? But <hi>Amyntor</hi> quickly delivered me, from my doubt, and my ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize: for the proof he offers, is from very vulgar Books; either miſtaken, or miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by him. He ſays, <q>The <hi>Manichees</hi> rejected the whole New Teſtament; the <hi>Ebionits</hi> or <hi>Nuzarens,</hi> who were the firſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:32695:37"/>Chriſtians, had a different Copy of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel from ours, and the <hi>Marcionits</hi> of St. <hi>Luke</hi>'s. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel was attributed, to <hi>Cerinthus; all</hi> the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of St. <hi>Paul</hi> were denyed by ſome, and a different Copy of 'em ſhown by others: and the ſeven Pieces we mentioned before, (he means, the Epiſtles of St. <hi>James,</hi> St. <hi>Jude,</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Peter,</hi> the ſecond and third of <hi>John,</hi> the Epiſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> and the Revelation) were refuſed a long time by all Chriſtians, with almoſt <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Conſent. <bibl>
                        <hi>P.</hi> 64, 65.</bibl>
                  </q> By all Chriſtians, <hi>with</hi> almoſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Conſent,</hi> is a Contradiction: for if by <hi>all</hi> Chriſtians, then with Univerſal Conſent; and if, only with <hi>almoſt</hi> Univerſal Conſent, then not by <hi>all</hi> Chriſtians. But it matters not; for we ſhall ſee, neither of 'em is True.</p>
               <p>When his hand was in, why did he not alſo (from as good Authority as he has a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the whole Canon of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) rout all the Authors of the Old Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament? For he might have ſaid from <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Haereſ Ebion.</hi> c. 13. p. 38. <q>Some <hi>Jews,</hi> called <hi>Nazarites,</hi> rejected Sacrifices: affirming that the Books of <hi>Moſes</hi> which we now have, are ſpurious, the true Writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> being altogether diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from our Copies of them; which true Writings are ſtill preſerved by their
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32695:38"/>Party. He repeats the ſame thing, <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cep.</hi> p. 134. Others who owned the five Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet refuſed all the other Books of the Old Teſtament; <hi>Epiphanius Haereſ. Sam.</hi> c. 2. To theſe laſt, for ſo much as concerns the Old Teſtament, were joined ſome <hi>Ebionits;</hi> ſaving that they approved the Book of <hi>Joſhua.</hi> 
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphan. Haereſ. Ebion.</hi> c. 13.</bibl>
                  </q> Let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all this; it will be undeniable, that almoſt all of it is falſe; and that little of it that is true, is of no weight.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Manichees,</hi> who ('tis pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) denyed all the New Teſtament; that is, denyed it to be written by the Authors whoſe Names it carries, or ſaid that at leaſt 'tis ſo very much interpolated and corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that 'tis now of no Authority: I will reſerve the Diſcuſſion of it, till we come alſo to the Philoſopher <hi>Celſus;</hi> who ſays that the Chriſtians had twice or thrice (or more times) altered their Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The <hi>Ebionits</hi> and <hi>Nazarens, ſays our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> had a different Copy of <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel, from ours.</q> Why does he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the <hi>Ebionits</hi> and <hi>Nazarens,</hi> as if they were one; and uſed the ſame Copy of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi>'s Goſpel? They were no more the ſame Sect of Chriſtians, than the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and the Quakers are: and were ſo far from uſing the ſame Copy of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:32695:38"/>that a common Enemy to both, witneſſes, the Copy of the <hi>Nazarens</hi> was (πληρέςατον) <hi>moſt perfect;</hi> but that of the <hi>Ebionits (Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teratum &amp; Mutilum</hi>) corrupted by Interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and defaced by Omiſſions. <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius Haereſ. Nazar.</hi> c. 9. <hi>Haereſ. Ebion.</hi> c. 13.</p>
               <p>This Goſpel of the <hi>Ebionits</hi> lacked the two firſt Chapters; namely the Genealogy of <hi>Joſeph</hi> from <hi>David,</hi> and the Hiſtory concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the three wiſe men out of the Eaſt: it began at the Baptiſm of <hi>John.</hi> As for the Additions, 'tis not ſaid expreſly what they were: likely, the Hiſtory of the Woman that was taken in Adultery; related in many Copies of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel, particularly in thoſe from which our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation was made. Alſo, ſome Anſwers of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, the Names alſo and Qualities of ſome of the Perſons he healed. All which might be added, from common Report of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our Saviour, and of others who knew the Facts and Perſons. Theſe things are ſaid to be in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Goſpel, either of the <hi>Nazarens</hi> or <hi>Ebionits;</hi> by <hi>Euſebius, Jerom, Auſtin, Photius,</hi> and others. It was a hard Cenſure by <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> to call 'em Adulterations: if no more can be objected to the Copy uſed by the <hi>Ebionits,</hi> than theſe traditional Memoirs added in ſome places, it were (if extant) to be highly valued.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:32695:39"/>
               <p>The omiſſion in their Copy, of the two firſt Chapters, was indeed the occaſion of great Diſputes and Heats among the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents. Not uncredibly, the <hi>Ebionits</hi> might follow the firſt Edition of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel, or his Hebrew Goſpel; which might begin at <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. that is, at the Baptiſm of <hi>John:</hi> but when <hi>Matthew</hi> publiſhed his Goſpel the ſecond time, <hi>Greek;</hi> he might add the Genealogy, and the Hiſtory of the Wiſe men. The <hi>Ebionits</hi> being all <hi>Jews,</hi> and underſtanding only the <hi>Hebrew</hi> (the <hi>Syro-Chaldaic</hi>) they adhered to the firſt Edition; rejecting the other: which alſo not being publiſhed (it may be) in <hi>Judaea,</hi> but from ſome other place; they might doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were really St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s. I can't ſee, what can be inferred from this, to the prejudice of Chriſtianity, or the Canon of Scripture; except by Perſons, who having a great mind to be Infidels, pleaſe themſelves with Trifles.</p>
               <p>But, <q>the <hi>Marcionites</hi> alſo had a different Copy, of the Goſpel of <hi>Luke.</hi>
                  </q> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, the Antients ſpeak of <hi>Marcion</hi>'s Copy of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> as adulterated; particularly <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen, Irenaeus, Juſtin Martyr, Tertullian:</hi> and laſtly <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> who has noted the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Alterations, and Subſtractions by <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion;</hi> they are theſe. He omits the two firſt Chapters, beginning his Goſpel with
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32695:39"/>the Preaching of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> Praecurſor to our Savior; and where the Prophets were alledged, or were ſpoken of, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenches it. The reſt, objected to <hi>Marci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>'s Copy, is but ill-grounded; for they are only <hi>various readings,</hi> not deſigned De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravations. <hi>Marcion</hi> intended by theſe chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to conform the Goſpel, <hi>to the Sentiments of his Party, concerning the Prophets:</hi> but he ſo did this, <hi>that</hi> the ſubſtance of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity was ſtill the ſame; and <hi>that, 'twas eaſy to ſee, on which ſide the Truth lay.</hi> This laſt is proved by the event; for the Marcionite Hereſy ſoon became extinct of it ſelf. An attempt to cut off ſuch large portions of this Goſpel, that were found in all the Copies uſed in the Churches, was too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant to ſucceed; or be long counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced, by any (ſober) men, unleſs ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by Intereſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marcion</hi> had been excommunicated by his own Father, who was a Biſhop, for For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication: hereupon, he went to <hi>Rome;</hi> but Letters from his Father, following him, they would not there receive him into Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. Enraged at this, he ſet up a new Sect; being a Learned Man, he procured not a few Followers, who made him their Biſhop: in this Station, he wrote divers Books; and publiſh'd a new Copy of the Goſpel by St. <hi>Luke,</hi> as alſo of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32695:40"/>making in both divers Alterations. He repented however, of theſe wicked en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors againſt: Truth, and Peace: he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled himſelf to the Church, undeceived moſt of his Followers; and would have reduced the reſt, but was prevented by Death. We have this Information, from the moſt Antient of the Latin Fathers; <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> Praeſcript. <hi>c.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>He alledges farther, <q>
                     <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel was attributed by ſome, to the Heretick <hi>Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus:</hi> all the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul</hi> were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed by ſome; and <hi>a different Copy</hi> ſhown of 'em, by others.</q> This (boaſted) <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Copy,</hi> is only the Copy of <hi>Marcion;</hi> voluntarily and piouſly <hi>retraced by himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That, any denyed St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles; meaning thereby, denyed them to be his; our Author will not prove, from any of the Antients. If by denying them, he means, rejected the Doctrine of 'em; we grant, they were denyed by the <hi>Ebionits:</hi> the witneſs againſt 'em is <hi>Epiphanius, Haereſ. Ebion.</hi> c. 13. The <hi>Ebionits</hi> were thoſe Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Chriſtians, who contended that, the Law was to be obſerved together with the Goſpel: <hi>Paul</hi> obtained againſt 'em a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, by the Apoſtles and Elders at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> recorded <hi>Acts</hi> 15. from <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. and often argues againſt their Opinion, in his Epiſtles. This occasioned their rejecting
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32695:40"/>thoſe Epiſtles; and a great many Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, againſt the Perſon of that Apoſtle: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other things, they deviſed that, <hi>Paul</hi> was <hi>a Gentile</hi> of <hi>Tarſus,</hi> and that miſſing an intended Marriage with the Daughter of a Prieſt at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he ſet himſelf to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Prieſthood and the Law.</p>
               <p>The ground on which St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Epiſtles were rejected by the <hi>Ebionits,</hi> namely <hi>that,</hi> in thoſe Epiſtles he denies that <hi>the Gentaic Chriſtians</hi> were obliged by the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> being condemned at the Council of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> mentioned <hi>Acts</hi> 15.24. and theſe Epiſtles being warranted, by ex preſs Authority of Sr. <hi>Peter,</hi> above quoted: me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks the <hi>Ebionits</hi> are here objected with as little color of Reaſon, as <hi>Marcion</hi> in the foregoing Paragraph.</p>
               <p>'Tis another Exception, that <q>
                     <hi>Johns</hi> Goſpel was aſcribed by ſome, to <hi>Cerinthus</hi> a great Heretick.</q> By the <hi>Alogians:</hi> but ſo, that this Party embraced in a little time the common Opinion, that; St. <hi>John</hi> was indeed the Writer of this Goſpel. <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſatum,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Sirmium,</hi> Heads of the <hi>Alogian</hi> party, even alledged for their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion the firſt Verſes of Sr. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel; and made not the leaſt doubt either of the Author or Authority of this Goſpel. <hi>Epiphan. Haereſ. Samoſat. &amp; Photin.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:32695:41"/>
               <p>He ſtill proceeds <q>The Epiſtles of <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Jude,</hi> the 2d of <hi>Peter,</hi> the 2d and 3d of <hi>John,</hi> that to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and the <hi>Rev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elation,</hi> were refuſed <hi>a long time,</hi> by Chriſtians, with <hi>almoſt</hi> univerſal Conſent.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The leaſt we can make of this, is that; <hi>the Majority</hi> of Chriſtians rejected theſe Writings, and that too <hi>a long time.</hi> But <hi>Euſebius,</hi> from whom our Author had his intelligence, ſays otherwiſe; he ſaith, <q>thoſe pieces are of the number <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but withal <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, i. e. <hi>Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid indeed,</hi> by we know not who; <hi>but received by the Generality.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Euſeb. <hi>H. E.</hi> l. 3. c. 25.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeems however they were rejected <hi>by ſome,</hi> and that alſo a <hi>long time.</hi> I anſwer, they were all received, as ſoon as the Churches had full communication with one another; by the Convention of Councils: which, for <hi>ſmall</hi> Books, <hi>containing nothing that if ſingular,</hi> was ſoon enough. They were received in the Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> by obſervation of our Author himſelf. Thoſe ſeven pieces having nothing, as I ſaid, that is ſingular; nothing that is wont to be alledged by the contending Parties, againſt one another: that Council was at perfect Liberty, whether they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, or reject them; they might do ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without diminution of Intereſt, or
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32695:41"/>of Reputation. I believe therefore, ſeeing the Scripture Canon was ſo ſufficient (in the Opinion of all Parties) without thoſe Books; they were not owned by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of that Council, but on moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing reaſons. Such as, <hi>that,</hi> they had certain Information that theſe Books were read, as Writings of the Apoſtles, in all Churches of <hi>antient</hi> Foundation; <hi>that</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves found 'em quoted (as Apoſtolick Compoſitions) <hi>in</hi> and <hi>from</hi> the times of the Apoſtles: alſo <hi>that</hi> there is in them a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Thoughts, and Expreſſion, and whatever elſe recommends to us the other Books of Scripture; to the Expreſſion, and Thoughts of the other Divine Books: or more briefly, they are written with the ſame kind of Spirit, that the undoubted portions of Scripture are. There might even be Teſtimony from ſome of the Churches, that; they had ſtill the firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed Copies of theſe Books and Epiſtles, with their Dates correſponding to the Age and Time of the Writers of them.</p>
               <p>Can any thing like to this, be ſaid for the (rejected) Books of the Catalogue? Were they ever approved, in any Council? Are any of them quoted, or pretended to be quoted, by Writers of the Apoſtolick Age? Is it not ſaid by thoſe Antients who had read 'em, and could belt judg of 'em;
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32695:42"/>they are compoſed with an Addreſs, and Air, quite different from that of the Inſpired Books; and are not only falſe in the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and Facts, but very fooliſh alſo? If ſome of 'em were read, in ſome Churches; was it nor, only till the Catholick Church began to fill with learned and able Perſons, who could make a Judgment? And when by theſe, they were diſcharged; was there any Contention for 'em, as there would certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have been, if the ſame (or like) reaſons could have been urged for 'em, as for the Books truly Canonical?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:32695:42"/>
               <head>Of the Philoſopher <hi>Celſus,</hi> and <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the <hi>Manichee.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Come therefore, to the laſt Refuge of the Anti-Chriſtian party. <q>Admitting that, the Books of the Canon were (for the main of 'em) written by the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and their Synergiſts: they have been however ſo changed, and that divers times; that now there is little, perhaps nothing left of 'em, in thoſe Books that ſtand for them, in our <hi>preſent</hi> Canon.</q> The witneſs for this, is the Philoſopher <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus;</hi> to whom (great) <hi>Origen</hi> immediatly anſwered. This Philoſopher, ſays <hi>Amyntor,</hi> informs us; that <q>
                     <hi>the Chriſtians,</hi> as if they were drunk, had changed the Writing of the Goſpel, three or four (or more) times: to the end they might deny what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is urged againſt them, as before retracted.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Philoſopher however doth not ſay, <hi>the Chriſtians have changed (or altered) their Goſpel;</hi> he ſays only τίνες πισέυοντων, <hi>ſome of thoſe called Believers, have altered the writing of the Goſpel. Origen</hi> makes us to underſtand the meaning of this, in his Anſwer to it; which is thus. <q>Indeed <hi>Marcion,</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinus,</hi>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:32695:43"/>and <hi>Lucanus,</hi> have preſumed to corrupt the Sacred Books. But what is that to Chriſtianity?</q> He intended here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; does the Church follow the (vitiated) Copies of <hi>Marcion,</hi> or of (the two <hi>Gnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics</hi>) <hi>Valentinus</hi> and <hi>Lucanus?</hi> are theirs the Books we ſhow, as our Rule of Faith and Manners? are theſe the Books read in the Churches of Chriſtians?</p>
               <p>In ſhort, they would prove: the Books of our <hi>preſent</hi> Canon are corrupted, and greatly altered from what they were; and how is it proved? Why, <hi>Marcion,</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinus,</hi> and <hi>Lucanus,</hi> publiſhed ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved Copies, that were rejected, ſo ſoon as they appeared, by all the Churches. Why do they not ſay, the Bibles of the Engliſh Church were corrupted in the Reign of K. <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Martyr?</hi> when the King's Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers publiſhed an Edition, in which the words of the Pſalmiſt were thus printed, <hi>The Fool hath ſaid in his Heart, there is a God:</hi> for which the Printers were fined 3000 <hi>l.</hi> and all the Copies ſuppreſt by the King's Order.</p>
               <p>Has <hi>Amyntor</hi> any Evidence, that the Copies of <hi>Valentinus, Lucanus</hi> and <hi>Marcion,</hi> or any of them, is the Copy now uſed by the Catholick Church; or doth not he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf certainly know the contrary? He hath no ſuch Evidence, and he knows the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary with certainty: therefore, he affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:32695:43"/>abuſed his Reader; and too much for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got that, a deceitful Management of ſuch Subjects as this, obliges his Reader to diſtruſt all he ſays, and more eſpecially his Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>We ſhall be troubled but with one Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer more, 'tis <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the <hi>Manichee;</hi> let us take the matter in our Author's own words. <q>Nay, as low as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s time; was there not <hi>a very conſiderable Sect,</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtians themſelves,</hi> I mean the <hi>Manichae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> who <hi>ſhewed other Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the genuinneſs of the</hi> whole <hi>New Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament?</hi> one of theſe called <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> &amp;c.</q> In theſe few Lines, are more Falſities, than Periods.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Manichees</hi> were never accounted <hi>a Sect of Chriſtians;</hi> and whether to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtians or not, they were far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>a very conſiderable Sect:</hi> nor did they ſhow <hi>other Scriptures,</hi> as written by Chriſt or his Apoſtles; nor deny the genuinneſs of <hi>the whole New Teſtament,</hi> or ſo much as of <hi>any Book</hi> of it. All the buſineſs is, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myntor</hi> knew not how to point the words of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> nor how to render them into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; his Tranſlation of 'em is not only falſe, but 'tis non-ſenſe.</p>
               <p>By the ſame figure of Speech, that he calls the <hi>Manichees, Chriſtians;</hi> he muſt alſo call the Mahometans, <hi>Christians:</hi> nay there is
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:32695:44"/>incomparably more reaſon, ſo to call the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than the former; but the latter were never ſo called by any, therefore neither may the former. <hi>Manchaeus</hi> and <hi>Mahomet</hi> equally pretended that, he was the <hi>Paraclet</hi> (or Comforter) promiſed to his Diſciples by our Saviour; in thoſe words recorded by St. <hi>John: If I go not, the Comforter</hi> (or <hi>Paraclet</hi>) <hi>will not come unto you; but if I depart, I will ſend him to you.</hi>—<hi>When he, the Spirit of Truth, is come, He will guide you into all Truth.</hi> John 16.7, 13. <hi>Mahomet</hi> innovated but little, comparatively, in the Articles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; <hi>Manichaeus</hi> ſubverted all things. He taught, and his (few) Followers believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</p>
               <p n="1">1. There are two Co-eternal Principles, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Hyle;</hi> the former the Author of all Good, the other of all Evil.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God very hardly defends his Frontiers, from the encroachments of Hyle: even ſome part of his Divine Subſtance is captivated, by Hyle; nor ſhall it ever be wholly releaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God is not the Creator of Mankind, but Nature.</p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:32695:44"/>
               <p n="4">4. The God of the Old Teſtament is a lying, and impotent Spirit; falſe and harſh to his Servants: and who was neither able, nor willing to protect, or do good to the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, or Church of the <hi>Jews;</hi> which ſerved him, as an Hand-maid her Miſtreſs.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Jeſus Chriſt was neither born, nor died; but is the off-ſpring of the Holy Spirit, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in the Earth, and ſubſiſting in all liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Creatures; as alſo in all Fruits and Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables: the viſible Jeſus was only a Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Patriarchs and Prophets of the Old Teſtament, were the moſt flagitious of all men; and ought not to be named, without ſome particular and remarkable Deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Souls are a part of the Subſtance of God; and when the Body dies, they enter into other Bodies of men, or of Beaſts, or Fiſh; or of ſome Tree, Herb, or Flower, as their deſert in the preſent Life hath been: except however, ſome few thorowly purified Souls, which re-aſcend into Heaven; where they live, and row in Boats of Light.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The Sun and Moon are to be adored.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:32695:45"/>
               <p>It is evident by theſe Articles of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichaean</hi> Creed, that; our Author might as well (or better) have ſaid, <q>There is a very conſiderable <hi>Sect of Chriſtians</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I mean <hi>the Mahometans;</hi> who ſhew other Scriptures, and deny the Books of our preſent Canon.</q> If this would be ridiculous; the other, <hi>a conſiderable Sect of Chriſtians, I mean the Manichees,</hi> is much more ſo.</p>
               <p>Well, let 'em be a Sect of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> yet they were not, as he ſaith, <hi>a very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Sect. St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who for <hi>nine years</hi> was of their Number, ſays; <hi>in tam exiguo, &amp; pene nullo Numero veſtro:</hi> i. e. you are a very few, and almoſt <hi>none at all.</hi> And again, <q>I confeſs, <hi>good</hi> Chriſtians are but few: but thoſe of our Denomination, who are <hi>really good,</hi> are vaſtly more than all you <hi>Manichees</hi> whether good or bad. <bibl>
                        <hi>Contr. Fauſium,</hi> l. 20. c. 23.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>They ſhall be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and a <hi>very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Sect.</hi> What then? Why, <hi>they ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed other Scriptures,</hi> different from thoſe that are read and uſed by the Church. If he means, they ſhew ſome Writings of <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeus;</hi> which, among them were valued, as the Scriptures of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles are eſteemed among Chriſtians: 'tis true indeed, but not to the purpoſe. No more than if he had ſaid; the <hi>Mahometans</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:32695:45"/>ſhow an <hi>Alchoran,</hi> as Chriſtians do a Bible: therefore the Bible is a ſpurious, ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Book, never wrote by the pretended Authors of it. The queſtion is, whether the Books of the New Teſtament are genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine; were indeed written by the Perſons whoſe names they bear? <hi>Amyntor</hi> anſwers, No; for the <hi>Manichees</hi> (a very conſiderable Sect of Chriſtians themſelves) ſhew <hi>other</hi> Scriptures. <hi>Plainly,</hi> if he means, they alſo ſhew Books written by the Patriarch of their Sect; 'tis a random Bolt: the enquiry not being, Whether the <hi>Manichees</hi> had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Books, which they followed; but, whether they pretended to prove, that the Chriſtian Bible is not genuin, by ſhewing other (different) Copies of it? And this, without doubt, <hi>Amyntor</hi> intended: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I anſwer; they never pretended to ſhew other Copies of the Chriſtian Bible, than thoſe in the Catholic Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> their Advocate, never ſays; ſuch a Text is not in our Copies: he ſays only, <hi>I believe 'tis foiſted into the Scripture-context, becauſe it is a manifeſt Falſhood.</hi> The two <hi>Paraclets, Manichaeus</hi> and <hi>Mahomet,</hi> were altogether unlearned; they both pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that, the Chriſtian Bible was in many places greatly corrupted: but this they proved, only by arguing againſt the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Paſſages, which they diſliked; not by
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:32695:46"/>producing other Copies, different from thoſe of the Church. In ſhort, the way they took, might prove the Scriptures of Chriſtians to be <hi>erroneous;</hi> but by no means to be ſpuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, interpolated, or <hi>not genuin.</hi> How this madneſs of the <hi>Paraclets,</hi> is to be anſwered, we ſhall conſider by and by; we muſt now examine what <hi>Amyntor</hi> has here added: he ſaith,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The <hi>Manichees</hi> not only ſhewed other Scriptures, but <hi>denied alſo the genuinneſs of the whole New Teſtament.</hi>
                  </q> He hath no witneſs of it; <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> whom he alledges, ſays the contrary. I don't deny, he has truly recited thoſe places of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> which he hath put into his Margin: but, as I intimated before, he hath neither ſeen, how to rightly point them, nor truly tranſlate them; and the reaſon of both (I imagine) was, he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lookt the Explanations that <hi>Fauſtus</hi> gives (in other Sections) of his meaning and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
               <p>Firſt, As to the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and of the other Apoſtles, both <hi>Fauſtus</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> own expreſly, they were allowed by the <hi>Manichees.</hi> Their words are theſe; <hi>Apoſtolum (Paulum) Accipis? Maxime.</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Do you receive</hi> Paul<hi>'s Epiſtles? Moſt readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and eſpecially.</hi> Lib. 11. c. 1.</q> Again, <q>
                     <bibl>Lib. 12. c. 24. <hi>Epiſtolas Apoſtolorum Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, Tenetis, Praedicatis.</hi>
                     </bibl> 
                     <hi>You read, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:32695:46"/>and even extol the Epiſtles of the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Goſpels, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> even diſdains, that it ſhould be queſtioned, whether they are received by the <hi>Manichees.</hi>
                  <q>If, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> by receiving the Goſpel, you mean <hi>obeying</hi> it; it is the Rule of my Life and Converſation. You (Catholics) pretend to receive the Goſpel, without giving any ſigns of it, in your manners: and you ask me, whether I receive it, who do all things that it requireth; even all things that might prevent ſuch a Queſtion. <bibl>
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 1, 2.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Elſwhere he deals more explicitly and clearly. <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 32. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</bibl> We receive as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Truth, all that <hi>the Son</hi> hath ſaid; and even all that was ſaid <hi>by his Apoſtles, after they were perfect and fully instructed.</hi> We paſs over, and neglect what the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles ſaid, while they were Novices and Ignorant; and what was objected to 'em, and not ſaid really by 'em: as alſo what has been falſly imputed to 'em, by <hi>the Writers; namely that,</hi> Jeſus was (foully) <hi>born</hi> of a Woman, was <hi>circumciſed</hi> like the <hi>Jews, offer'd Sacrifice</hi> like the <hi>Gentiles, was baptized</hi> in a ſordid manner, was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about and <hi>miſerably tempted</hi> by the Devil. Theſe few things excepted, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all their Quotations out of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32695:47"/>
                     <hi>the old Testament;</hi> we receive <hi>the Writers,</hi> [he means the four Evangeliſts,] and all they have recorded, or taught in their Books: more eſpecially, we receive the <hi>Myſtical Crucifixion;</hi> with the Precepts, Parables, and whole Divine Word of Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>Amyntor</hi> had attended to theſe Paſſages, he would have perceived, how the words of this <hi>Manichee</hi> (which he cites) are to be Pointed, and Tranſlated into the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Let us firſt ſee, how <hi>Amyntor</hi> reads, and renders 'em.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solius Filii putatis Teſtamentum non potuiſſe corrumpi; ſolum non habere aliquid quod in ſe debeat improbari:</hi> praeſertim quod <hi>nec ab ipſo ſcriptum conſtat, nec ab ejus Apoſtolis: ſed longo poſt tempore a quibuſdam incerti nominis viris, qui, ne ſibi non haberetur ſides ſcribenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quae neſcirent, partim Apoſtolorum nomina, parting corum qui Apoſtolos ſecuti viderentur, ſcriptorum ſuorum frontibus indiderunt, aſſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes ſecuncdumeos ſe ſcripſiſſe quae ſcripſerint.</hi> He engliſhes it, thus. <q>You think, that of all the Books in the world, <hi>the Teſtament of the Son</hi> only could not be corrupted, that it alone contains nothing which ought to be diſallowed; <hi>eſpecially when it appears, that it was neither written by himſelf, nor his Apoſtles,</hi> but a long time after by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain obſcure Perſons, who, leſt no credit
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:32695:47"/>ſhould be given to the Stories they told of what they could not know, did prefix to their Writings partly the names of the Apoſtles, and partly of thoſe who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the Apoſtles; affirming that what they wrote themſelves, was written by theſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>We ſhall ſee preſently, Light and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are not more contrary, than this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Books that make the preſent Canon of the New Teſtament, is to the real Opinion of <hi>Faustus,</hi> and the intention of his words in the Latin: but now I will only take notice that, this Tranſlation is a pure piece of Jargon; it offers to prove a certain point, by a Conſideration quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it. It repreſents the <hi>Manichee</hi> as ſaying; you (Catholies) think <hi>the Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Son contains nothing that may be diſallowed: becauſe</hi> it appears that, neither himſelf nor his Apoſtles wrote it; but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain obſcure Fellows, who to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves believed in matters <hi>of which they knew nothing,</hi> put the Names of the Apoſtles to their own Flams and Forgeries. I demand now of <hi>Amyntor,</hi> was this a Reaſon, fit to prove that the Teſtament of the Son has <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it that can be diſallowed;</hi> even this, 'twas written by obſcure Fellows, who hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing feigned theſe Matters, ſet to 'em the Names of the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors?
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:32695:48"/>'Tis a Reaſon, that moſt plainly overthrows the Propoſition, which it was to confirm; in ſhort, 'tis a Bull, a Contradiction, and Nonſenſe. 'Tis as if I ſhould ſay, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> is like to live this three ſeven years; for he is very infirm, and dying (in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) every day.</p>
               <p>Well; let us again ſet down the Latin of the <hi>Manichee,</hi> and Pointing it right, ſee what ſenſe it will make.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solius Filii, putatis, Teſtamentum non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuiſſe corrunipi; ſolum non habere aliquid, quod in ſe debeat improbari?</hi> Praeſertim, quod <hi>nec ab ipſo ſcriptum conſtat, nec ab ejus Apoſtolis; ſed longo poſt tempore, a quibuſdam incerti no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis viris: qui, ne ſibi non haberetur Fides, ſeribentibus quae neſcirent; partim Apoſtolorum nomina, partim corum qui Apoſtolos ſecuti vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derentur, ſcriptorum ſuorum frontibus indide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt; aſſeverantes, ſecundum eos ſe ſcripſiſſe quae ſcripſerunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be Engliſhed thus. <q>Do ye think <hi>that,</hi> of all Books in the World, only <hi>the Teſtament of the Son</hi> could not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved; and <hi>that,</hi> it alone contains no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that can be gainſaid? <hi>Eſpecially, that of it</hi> (or <hi>that part of it</hi>) which not only, was not written by himſelf; but not by his Apoſtles: but a long time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by certain obſcure Fellows. Who, leſt no Credit ſhould be given to what
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:32695:48"/>they wrote, concerning matters which they could not know, put the names of Apoſtles and their Succeſſors, in the front of their Books; affirming that, what they wrote themſelves, was written by thoſe Apoſtles.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He ſpeaks here of the Acts, Revelations, Epiſtles, Goſpels <hi>of the Catalogue;</hi> he ſays, the genuine <hi>Teſtament of the Son</hi> is much depraved by theſe ſpurious Books: which were contrived and publiſhed long after the deceaſe of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles that wrote the Books truly Canonical; by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Wretches, that put to their feigned Goſpels and Acts the names of <hi>Andrew, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Philip, Bartholomew,</hi> and other Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and their Succeſſors. Briefly, <hi>Fauſtus</hi> meant not in the leaſt, to ſay; the <hi>Books of the Canon</hi> are falſly intitled to the Apoſtles, and Evangeliſts, whoſe names they bear: but that, the <hi>Teſtament of the Son</hi> has been vitiated, and diſgraced, by divers <hi>other</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpels, Acts, Epiſtles, meaning <hi>thoſe of the Catalogue;</hi> which never were the Works of <hi>true</hi> Apoſtles, but of certain Botchers, who ſtitching together ſome flying Reports, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed their wares to ſale, under the names of ſome of the Apoſtles, and of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Succeſſors.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:32695:49"/>
               <p>His other Citation, out of <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> is no better; nor (upon the main) better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by him: it is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Multa à Majoribus veſtris, eloquiis Domini noſtri inſerta ſunt verba, quae nomine ſignata ipſius cum ejus fide non congruunt; praeſertim quia,</hi> ut jam ſaepe probatum à Nobis eſt, <hi>nec ab ipſo haec ſunt, nec ab ejus Apoſtolis ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta: ſed multa, poſt eorum aſſumptionem à ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcio quibus, &amp; ipſis inter ſe non concordanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Semi-judaeis, per famas opinioneſque com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perta ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He renders it in theſe words. <q>Many things were foiſted by your Anceſtors, into the Scripture of our Lord; which, tho marked with his Name, agree not with his Faith. And no wonder, ſince, <hi>as thoſe of our Party have already frequently proved,</hi> theſe things were neither written by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf nor his Apoſtles: but ſeveral matters after their deceaſe were pick'd up from Stories and flying Reports, by I know not what ſet of Half-Jews; and theſe alſo not agreeing among themſelves.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Reach me the Ferula, for they are School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boys Miſtakes. In this place, <hi>Jam</hi> is not, <hi>already;</hi> or <hi>ſaepe, frequently:</hi> much leſs is <hi>à Nobis, thoſe of our Party,</hi> which it never ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies; and had <hi>Fauſtus</hi> intended to ſay <hi>by thoſe of our Party,</hi> he would have ſaid <hi>a Noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris.</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:32695:49"/>His words <hi>Jam ſaepe probatum eſt a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis,</hi> were thus meant, <hi>As I have but now proved, by divers Examples:</hi> for he refers to the ſeveral Examples he had juſt before given, of <hi>Doctrines and Facts, which (as he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and ſuppoſed he had proved it) were added to the Goſpels of</hi> Matthew <hi>and</hi> Luke; only he ſpeaks of himſelf, as Authors are commonly wont, in the Plural number, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>à Nobis</hi> for <hi>à me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But from all this, <hi>Amyntor</hi> infers, and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately</hi> ſubjoins; <hi>ſince therefore the</hi> Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeans <hi>rejected the whole New Teſtament,</hi> &amp;c. You are a great deal too haſty, Son; your Friends the <hi>Manichees</hi> received the whole <hi>Genuine</hi> Canon of the New Teſtament: they rejected only, the corrupt part of <hi>the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Son,</hi> even the Goſpels and other pieces of your Catalogue; and <hi>ſome Paſſages which (they pretended) had been unduly inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Epiſtles and Goſpels of the Canon;</hi> nor will you ever make more of your Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> by whatſoever ſtretching and ſtraining them.</p>
               <p>By this it appears, how much our Author is pleas'd with Hyperbolies; he ſays, <q>A <hi>very conſiderable</hi> Sect, of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I mean the <hi>Manichees,</hi> ſhewed <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Scriptures, and denied the Genuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>the whole New Teſtament.</hi>
                  </q> He ſhould have ſaid, a <hi>ſmall Party, leſs</hi> Chriſtians by
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:32695:50"/>much than the Mahometans, denied the genuinneſs of <hi>thoſe parts</hi> of the Goſpels and Epiſtles; where the Books of the Old Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament are cited: as alſo where mention is made of the Genealogy, Birth, Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Baptiſm, or Death of Chriſt; becauſe they ſuppoſed, Chriſt was God only, and Man not at all; and that it was unworthy of God to be born, tempted, baptized, or put to death.</p>
               <p>The Objection however hath ſtill ſome force: 'tis thus far true, that ſome there were who ſaid, the Books of the Canon are not now altogether ſincere; they are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by divers Additions. Yes, the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichees</hi> ſaid ſo: and if our Author had pleaſed, he could have told us, by what Arguments they were convinced of their Impertinence and Folly; it would very well have become him, to have taken that (little) farther pains.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:32695:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Of the (pretended) Interpola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Additions, in the Books of the Canon.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Manichees</hi> ſaid: The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Spirit of Truth, promiſed to the Faithful by Chriſt, even the bleſſed <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeus,</hi> was ſent by God, to inform his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and all other his People, concerning his farther Will and good-pleaſure: as alſo to inſtruct them, what of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is genuine, and to be received by all; and what to be rejected, as either <hi>miſtaken</hi> by the Apoſtles yet unperfect, or ſince <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> by others to the Writings of the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and Evangeliſts.</p>
               <p>Being asked, What theſe Miſtakes, and Additions were? They anſwered; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is ſaid of the Genealogy, Birth, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, Temptation, and real Death of Chriſt; all quotations out of, and all honourable mention any where made concerning the Patriarchs, Prophets and Writers of the Old Teſtament. When demanded, farther; on <hi>what grounds</hi> they preſumed to reject, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Old Teſtament, or ſuch large por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the New? They replyed; <hi>Moſes</hi> has blaſphemed Chriſt, in thoſe words of his,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:32695:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>He that is hanged, is accurſed of God,</hi> Deut. 21.23.</p>
               <p>The God of the Old Teſtament, <hi>ſaid the</hi> Manichees, appears to have been a wicked, and impotent Spirit; chiefly, by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the ſlaughter of <hi>innocent</hi> Beaſts, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>guilty</hi> Men: and by dealing ſo harſhly, with his Slaves the <hi>Jews.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, his Prophets alſo are to be rejected: as for the ſame reaſon we would (and do) reject the Prieſts and Prophets, of the other evil Gods of the Nations.</p>
               <p>It is not to be thought, <hi>ſo they went on,</hi> that, Jeſus Chriſt commended, or his Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles cited, the writings of the Prophets and Servants of ſuch an impure God: no, all ſuch Citations and Commendations have been (undoubtedly) added, by certain Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that were half Jews and half Chriſtians, to the Goſpels and Epiſtles of the New Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament. So alſo was whatſoever is found in thoſe Books concerning the Genealogy, Birth, Circumciſion, Temptation, Baptiſm, or Death of Chriſt. Who being God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwent all theſe things: only in appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and by that <hi>Phantom</hi> (which the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar took to be real Chriſt) that repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him: even as Angels ſeem to have Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to be clothed, to eat and drink; when in truth they neither drink nor eat, nor are clothed, nor have real Bodies.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:32695:51"/>
               <p>This was the <hi>Manichaean</hi> Doctrine, with reſpect to the Chriſtian Religion, and Books of the New Teſtament; to which they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the eight Articles, before mentioned, taught 'em by <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> and his Second <hi>Adimantus,</hi> and maintained by <hi>Fauſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Says St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> One may eaſily make ſhort work, with this wild People. For whereas all depends on the Authority of <hi>Manichaeus:</hi> I deſire to know, how they prove he was that Paraclet; that Spirit of Truth, that was to lead us into all truth; promiſed by our Saviour? They anſwer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, out of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel; <hi>I will ſend the Comforter</hi> (or Paraclet) <hi>the Spirit of Truth, who ſhall lead you into all Truth:</hi> but they ſay withal, the Goſpels (and other Books of the New Teſtament) are ſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, that there is no (abſolute) truſting to 'em. We demand a Witneſs, on behalf of their Paraclet: they alledg one, out of our own New Teſtament; which (they ſay) is a falſe and corrupted Witneſs. Any Book or other Witneſs, convict of Falſhood and Corruption, in bearing its Teſtimony; eſpecially, of <hi>many</hi> Corruptions, and Falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; is uncapable of ſtanding again as a Witneſs (merely on its own Credit) in whatſoever Caſe. Briefly, by accuſing the New Teſtament, as a Book in ſo many places
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:32695:52"/>corrupted; they deprive themſelves of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever benefit, that might ariſe to them, from its Teſtimony.</p>
               <p>But to forgive to Fools, an overſight, that deſtroys their whole Cauſe: St. <hi>John</hi> ſhall be a ſincere Evangeliſt, in ſpeaking of the Spirit, or Paraclet; tho the other Books and Writers, and he himſelf in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, hath been miſtaken, or is corrupted by others. But as this is the Evangeliſt, who has foretold the ſending of the Paraclet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; ſo he hath alſo foretold <hi>the time</hi> when he ſhould come: for he ſaith, John 7.39. <hi>The Holy Spirit was not yet given, becauſe Jeſus was not yet glorified.</hi> The reaſon, it ſeems, that the Spirit was not <hi>then</hi> given, was; becauſe Jeſus not being yet glorified, that is, not departed from his Diſciples into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, 'twas not neceſſary he ſhould be yet given: but when <hi>Jeſus</hi> was dead, raiſed, and aſcended into Heaven; then was the time to ſend forthwith the Paraclet. According<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we find in the Acts of the Apoſtles, in the ſecond Chapter of thoſe Acts; fifty days after our Savior's Reſurrection, and but ten days after his Aſcenſion <hi>into Glory,</hi> the Spirit (the promiſed Paraclet) deſcended on the Apoſtles. What room now is here for <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus,</hi> or for <hi>Manichaeus?</hi> The Spirit of Truth was to come, ſo ſoon as Chriſt was
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:32695:52"/>gone from his Apoſtles, and entred into <hi>the Glory</hi> deſigned for him; but <hi>Montanus</hi> came not till 170 years after Chriſt was glorified, and <hi>Manichaeus</hi> (as if our Savior had ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forgot his promiſe) not till the year 275.</p>
               <p>The Father goes on. I will take no Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of all this; I will otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you, that your Patriarch was a Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, and a Liar. He ſays, the Books of the New Teſtament have been corrupted, by Additions made to 'em: certain <hi>Half-Jews</hi> have added Citations out of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and falſe Tales concerning the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage, Nativity, Circumciſion, Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Baptiſm, Death of Chriſt: all which are impoſſible flams, becauſe he that was God, and not Man at all, could neither do nor ſuffer any of theſe things. Therefore I ask, did <hi>Manichaeus</hi> alledg, or can you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, any Copies of the New Teſtament; wherein all theſe things are not found? When ſome Copies of a Book have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that others have not; there is either Miſtake, or Fraud, in one or other of them: and we are wont in that Caſe, to conſult more Copies; eſpecially thoſe that are An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and thoſe that are preſerved in Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or in Archives that have been long and religiouſly kept. From the greateſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:32695:53"/>number of Copies, and thoſe that are moſt Antient; and that have been kept in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where they could not eaſily or likely be violated, by Additions or Subſtractions; we judg reaſonably, and ſafely, concerning the Copies that are ſuſpected or queſtioned. I pray, therefore, ſhow us, or refer us to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, where theſe (pretended) Additions are not read; in what Libraries, in what Archives of Churches or Sects, are ſuch Copies to be found? But as you never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, to any ſuch Copies; ſo <hi>'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, there ſhould be any ſuch.</hi> For the New Teſtament being in the hands of <hi>all</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and read in <hi>all</hi> Churches: theſe (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended) Additions could never be made, and leaſt of all in the publick Books of the Churches; without being obſerved, known, and oppoſed in their very firſt appearance. Are there ſo many thouſand Churches, and diſtant from one another ſo many thouſand Miles, under the Inſpection of ſo many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct Biſhops and Presbyters; nay and of ſeveral Princes: and could all theſe Books, think you, be corrupted, without their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving it? Or what is as impoſſible, or rather <hi>more</hi> impoſſible; by common Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? For are ſo many wont to agree, to falſe Additions, to their Books of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion?</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:32695:53"/>
               <p>Theſe are ſome of the Arguments, of that diſcerning Father, againſt <hi>Faustus,</hi> and his Patriarchs <hi>Manichaeus</hi> and <hi>Adimantus:</hi> I am of opinion, we have here given to <hi>Amyntor,</hi> as 'tis ſaid in the Proverb, <hi>A Rowland for his Oliver. Faustus</hi> is not ſo conſiderable, but that St. <hi>Austin</hi> appears much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable. In <hi>Faustus,</hi> one may ſee an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable</hi> Infidelity, a precipitate and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded</hi> Scepticiſm: in St. <hi>Austin,</hi> Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Faith, led on by Judgment; a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enlightned by Learning, and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>I omit what he ſaith, of the God of the Old Teſtament; of the Patriarchs and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; as forein to my preſent Undertaking and Subject: I only obſerve farther, that; What he hath ſo well argued againſt <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> is no leſs effectual, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the third <hi>Paraclet, Mahomet,</hi> who aroſe after St. <hi>Austin.</hi> If <hi>Montanus</hi> in the year after Chriſt 170, or <hi>Manichaeus</hi> in 275, could not be the promiſed <hi>Paraclet;</hi> becauſe the Evangeliſt, on whoſe Authority their Claims are founded, ſets a time (<hi>when Jeſus ſhall be glorified</hi>) that diſagrees ſo widely from the time of their appearance, and agrees ſo exactly with the time of the deſcent of the Holy Spirit on the Apoſtles: I ſay, if for this ſo clear Reaſon; neither
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:32695:54"/>
                  <hi>Montanus</hi> in 170, nor <hi>Manichaeus</hi> in 255, could be that <hi>Paraclet</hi> that was to lead into all Truth: much leſt could <hi>Mahomet</hi> be he, in the year after our Lord 612; ſeeing neither did <hi>Mahomet</hi> pretend to any other ground, for his Novelties, but thoſe words in St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel concerning a future <hi>Paraclet.</hi> See Father <hi>Simon</hi>'s <hi>Belief and Customs of the Eastern Nations,</hi> Chap. 15. When the ſame Impoſtor, as his Predeceſſor <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes the Bible of Chriſtians; as having many corrupt Additions, and other Falſifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; he is unanſwerably refuted by the ſame Conſiderations, that were objected, (before) to <hi>Manichaeus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SIR,</hi> I have now anſwered as fully as (I think) is needful, to a Book; which, you tell me, is ſo much magnified by the Anti-Chriſtian Party about Town. They ſay, this Book has ſo diſcovered, and laid bare, the (unſound) Foundations of Chriſtianity; that 'tis now to be blown down by the very weakeſt Breath: and <hi>that,</hi> if an Anſwer any what valuable, be made to it; the Author will take occaſion thereat, by <hi>new</hi> and <hi>more</hi> and <hi>greater</hi> Authorities, to level all <hi>revealed Imposture</hi> with the very Ground. He can level nothing by ſuch an attempt, but his own Reputation; nor do I think, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:32695:54"/>theſe impious Boaſts, of that Party of men. It may be queſtioned, whether he had any formed Deſign, to attack Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, by this Book: it ſeems rather, that, when his Paſſions were up, againſt Mr. <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hal,</hi> he inadvertedly dropt theſe Exceptions and Doubts, of which ſome make ſo bad uſe; or (rather) ſtrain ſuch malignant Conſequences, from them. To cut out work for Mr. <hi>Blackhal,</hi> with whom he was ſo much diſpleaſed; he diſcharged upon him, whatſoever occurred to his Memory, from firſt Antiquity; with intent to engage him in laborious, difficult, and unwelcome Searches. However it be, it appears he is a Perſon of great Abilitys, and Addreſs, in matters of this kind: and it were to be wiſh'd, men of very diſtinguiſhing Parts and Sufficiency, were not made Enemies to the Church, or to the Public, either by being abuſed, or becauſe they are neglected. You ſhall not awe ſuch Perſons by your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, or your Severities; when even ſuch mean Rogues as Houſe-breakers, and High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way-men, are not ſcared by the Gibbet and Gallows. The only effect to be expected, from neglect of, or harſhneſs toward ſuch, is that, they go at length into the intereſts of ſome diſaffected Party, or erect a new one: after which, whatſoever becomes of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:32695:55"/>them, the Public and the Church are ſure to be infinitly more loſers; than it would have coſt to gain, and to aſſure them, to the Public. But, <hi>manum de tabulâ</hi> for who made me a Counſellor to the Church, or the Public? You will pleaſe, Sir, to believe that, I am, with great Tenderneſs and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your aſſured Friend, STEPHEN NYE.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Sept.</hi> 29. 1699.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:32695:55"/>
            <p>There is room, in this Leaf, for two Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za's by Sir <hi>William Davenant:</hi> Which are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the Subject, that we have been treating.</p>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>In the dark Walk, to our last Home, deſign'd;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>'Tis ſafe, by</hi> well-inſtructed <hi>Guides to go:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leſt we</hi> in Death <hi>too late the Science find</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of what</hi> in Life <hi>'twas poſſible to know.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>And if they ſay (while daily ſome renew</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſputes) your Oracles are</hi> doubtful <hi>ſtill;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Like thoſe of Old: yet more regard is due</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To Pains, where ſo uneaſy is the skill.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="abstract">
            <pb facs="tcp:32695:56"/>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:32695:56"/>
            <head>AN ABSTRACT Of the foregoing DISPUTATION.</head>
            <p>THE Controverſy hath been, partly concerning the Books of <hi>the Canon,</hi> and partly concerning thoſe of <hi>the Catalogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Books of the Canon, <hi>Amyntor</hi> ſays;</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <q>
                     <hi>ALL the Authors of the Canon, were wholly ſtrangers to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers Writings.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>I have proved on the contrary, that, Mark's Goſpel is but an Abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of the Goſpel by <hi>Matthew; that,</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> (in the firſt Verſes of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:32695:57"/>his Goſpel) commends the Goſpels of <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark: that,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the Goſpels of theſe three for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Evangeliſts; and wrote his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, only by way of Supplement to theirs: <hi>that,</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> commends the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul;</hi> and ſignifie at the ſame time, that they were <hi>commonly</hi> read, and a bad Uſe made of them by ſome: <hi>that,</hi> the Catholick Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, (by <hi>James, Peter, Jude,</hi> and <hi>John;</hi>) the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation;</hi> being written either to whole Nations, or to all Chriſtians, were certainly publiſh'd as ſoon as written.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <q>
                     <hi>At leaſt, the Clergy and Churches were unacquainted with the Books of the New Teſtament, till</hi> 130 <hi>years after Chriſt.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>I have ſhown they were quoted by all the (extant) Writers of thoſe Times; by <hi>Barnabas, Herinas, Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Polycarp, Clemens Romanus:</hi> and by
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:32695:57"/>ſome not Extant, as <hi>Papias</hi> of <hi>Hiera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis</hi> in the year 110. Farther <hi>that,</hi> the four Goſpels, the Acts, Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Catholick Epiſtles, and Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> being written for general Information, or to whole Churches or Nations; they were <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to be publiſh'd,</hi> and <hi>publiſh'd as ſoon as written:</hi> and <hi>that,</hi> 'tis a very preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and withal an unreaſonable ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that, the Clergy and Churches were ignorant of <hi>the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd Books</hi> of their Religion. <hi>That,</hi> the contrary (in truth) is evident: for as early as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>'s time, the Churches entertained <hi>a Reader;</hi> beſides the Deacons, Presbyters, and Biſhop; who read the Old and New Teſtaments to the Aſſembly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <q>
                     <hi>It was impoſſible, when the Books of the Canon firſt appeared, to diſtinguiſh them from ſpurious Goſpel, Acts, Epiſtles, and Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; which were alſo entitled to the Apoſtles.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:32695:58"/>
                  <p>I have replyed, there was nothing more obvious or eaſy to the <hi>then</hi> Churches, than to diſtinguiſh them, with abſolute certainty; by their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement or Diſagreement with the Doctrine, and Hiſtory of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; which <hi>thoſe</hi> Churches had but juſt before received by word of Mouth, from the Apoſtles and other firſt (miraculous) Preachers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Different Copies were ſhown of all the Canonical Books, from the very firſt: the</hi> Nazarens <hi>and</hi> Ebionits <hi>had a Goſpel of St.</hi> Matthew, <hi>different from ours; the</hi> Marcionits <hi>of St.</hi> Luke, <hi>and of the Epiſtles of</hi> Paul.</q>
                  <p>I have anſwer'd, <hi>Marcion</hi> was ſo ingenuous, as to retract his vitiated Copies of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, and of St. <hi>Luke</hi>'s Goſpel; the Copy of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> uſed by the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> was (ſay the Antients) πληρέςατον, <hi>moſt perfect:</hi> the <hi>Ebionite</hi> Copy, being probably St.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:32695:58"/>
                     <hi>Matthew</hi>'s <hi>firſt</hi> (or Hebrew) Edition of his Goſpel, did indeed want the two firſt Chapters; and in time they had added ſome <hi>Traditional Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs,</hi> from the Witneſs of ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples that had ſeen the Facts, and knew the Perſons; it were to be wiſh'd, we had ſtill this Copy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <q>
                     <hi>The Books of the Canon were imputed by ſome very conſiderable Sects of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, not to the Apoſtles whoſe names they bear; but either to Hereticks, or to a ſet of Half-Jews and Half-Chriſtians, who had written them only from hearſay and flying Reports.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>I have evinced, that, only the Goſpel of <hi>John</hi> was ever miſlayed: and <hi>that,</hi> the <hi>Alogians</hi> ſoon ſaw their Error in the Caſe; not only receiving that Goſpel, but receiving it alſo (with all other Sects and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es) <hi>as St.</hi> John<hi>'s. That,</hi> the <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees</hi> (the other <hi>conſiderable Sect of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:32695:59"/>Chriſtians</hi> intended in the Objection) owned our four Goſpels, the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of <hi>Paul,</hi> all the Catholick Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and all other Books of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non: in ſhort that, <hi>Amyntor</hi> certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (and inadvertently enough) miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took the meaning of the Author (<hi>Fauſtus</hi> the <hi>Manichee</hi>) whom he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>6.</head>
                  <q>
                     <hi>The Philoſopher</hi> Celſus <hi>complains that, the Chriſtians had alter'd their Goſpel, three or four, or more times.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Celſus,</hi> I have ſaid, meant this, of the Copies of <hi>Marcion,</hi> and of <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi> and <hi>Lucanus:</hi> which never were uſed in the Churches; but at their firſt appearance were detected, and rejected by all Churches.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:32695:59"/>
               <head>Of the Books of the Catalogue, he ſaith;</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <q>
                     <hi>MANY of 'em have rather been ſuppreſt, by the ſtrongeſt ſide in the Church, than loſt: and that, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably they were the genuin Works of the Apoſtles.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>I have granted, divers of 'em might be the real Works of thoſe whoſe names they bore; and that our loſs of them is to be regretted: but the whole body of Learning has ſuffer'd extremely, by the loſs of ſome of the beſt Books in every Science and Art. Notwithſtanding, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alledged by the Antients againſt <hi>many</hi> of them, are ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us that, there was juſt cauſe to ſlight, and even to ſuppreſs them.</p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:32695:60"/>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <q>
                     <hi>The Epiſtles of</hi> Barnabas, Ignatius, Polycarp, Clemens Romanus, <hi>and the Paſtor of</hi> Hermas, <hi>were eſteemed by the Antients to be a good Scripture, as any part of the New Teſtament: they were received, by the ſoundeſt of the Antients; who at the ſame time rejected divers Books of our preſent Canon, namely, the</hi> Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>the Epiſtle to the</hi> Hebrews, <hi>the Epiſtle of</hi> Jude, <hi>the ſecond of</hi> Peter, <hi>and the ſecond and third of</hi> John.</q>
                  <p>But I have produced unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Teſtimony, of the Antients; that theſe leſſer pieces of the Canon were always received by <hi>the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> of Churches and Chriſtians: and that, when they were owned in the Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> 'twas on very good grounds; on the <hi>same</hi> Reaſons which convinced 'em of the genuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the other Books of the New Teſtament. As to <hi>Barnabas, Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Polycarp, Hermas,</hi> and <hi>Clemens Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus;</hi>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:32695:60"/>they were conſidered indeed as pious and well-minded Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but were read no otherwiſe, but as we now read <hi>in our Churches</hi> the <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Books of the Old Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament: which, for all that, we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly deny to be <hi>Divine Scripture;</hi> and many think them not very Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying or Profitable, eſpecially ſome of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <q>
                     <hi>The principal (Ante-nicen) Fathers quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted divers Goſpels, Epiſtles, and Acts of the Catalogue; as Scripture, and Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical: and this is all that can be ſaid, for the Books of the Canon; and more than can be truly ſaid, for ſome of them.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>I have alledged the very words of thoſe Fathers: it appears, they never cite the Books of the Catalogue, as <hi>Divine Scripture;</hi> and in reciting the Books of the <hi>true</hi> Scripture-Canon and of the Apoſtles, they <hi>always</hi> omit <hi>all</hi> the Goſpels and other Books of the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:32695:61"/>Catalogue. I grant however, that; the mere Terms <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Canonical</hi> were at firſt applied to all Eccleſiaſtical Books, that were judged Orthodox; as alſo to the Apocryphal Books of the Old Teſtament; to diſtinguiſh them from the Moral pieces, of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philoſophers: but the (alledged) Fathers have made us know the great difference, they put between mere <hi>Scripture,</hi> and <hi>Divine Scripture;</hi> between <hi>Canonical,</hi> and <hi>Inſpired.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Nam pudet, haec opprobria Nobis</l>
                  <l>Et dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe Refelli.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:32695:61"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>ALL the Works of the late Reverend and Learned <hi>William Bates,</hi> D. D. and ſome Account of him in a Funeral Sermon by Mr. <hi>John How,</hi> with an Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betical Table to the whole, are propoſed to be printed in a large Folio, on an extraordinary Paper and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, at twenty five Shillings in quires; they that ſubſcribe for ſix to have a ſeventh gratis: The Book to contain about 250 Sheets. They that are willing to incourage ſo uſeful an Undertaking, are deſired to ſend in their Subſcriptions with all ſpeed to</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jonathan Robinſon</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard; or to</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brabazon Aylmer</hi> at the three Pigeons againſt the <hi>Royal-Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Edition of Mr. <hi>Poole</hi>'s Annotations on the Bible is now in the Preſs, and will be ſhortly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: it is propos'd to Subſcribers at fifty Shillings in Quires, tho printed on a much better Paper than the former Edition. They that ſubſcribe for ſix to have a ſeventh. Subſcriptions are taken by the ſame Perſons.</p>
            <p>A Complete Hiſtory or Survey of die various Methods and Diſpenſations of Religion, from the beginning of the World to the conſummation of all things, as repreſented in the Old and New Teſtament. In which the Almighty's Wiſdom is diſplayed in the Government of the Church, thro the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ages of it. In 2 Vol. By <hi>John Edwards,</hi> D.D. Trice 10 <hi>s.</hi> Sold by <hi>J. Robinſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32695:62"/>
            <p>A Complete Hiſtory of the Canon and Writers of the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, by way of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertation: with uſeful Remarks on that Subject. <hi>Vol. I. On the Books of the Old Teſtament.</hi> By <hi>L. E. Du Pin,</hi> Doctor of the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> and <hi>Regius</hi> Profeſſor of Philoſophy in <hi>Paris.</hi> Done from the French. Price 12 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcourſes concerning Government, by <hi>Algernon Sidney,</hi> Son to <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> and Ambaſſador from the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Charles Guſtavus</hi> King of <hi>Sweden. Publiſhed from an Original Manuſcript of the Author.</hi> Price 15 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A complete Collection of the Hiſtorical, Political, and Miſcellaneous Works of <hi>John Milton,</hi> both Engliſh and Latin. With ſome Papers never before publiſh'd. In 3 Vol. To which is prefix'd, The Life of the Author, containing, beſides the History of his Works, ſeveral extraordinary Characters of Men and Books, Sects, Parties, and Opinions. Price 35 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The General Hiſtory of <hi>England</hi> both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, from the earlieſt Accounts of Time to the Reign of his preſent Majeſty King <hi>William</hi> III. Taken from the moſt antient Records, Manuſcripts and Historians. Containing the Lives of the Kings, and Memorials of the moſt Eminent Perſons both in Church and State. With the Foundations of the Noted Monaſteries, and both the Univerſities. Vol. I. By <hi>James Tyrrel</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Price 20 <hi>s.</hi> The ſecond Volume is in the Preſs, and will ſhortly be publiſhed.</p>
            <p>An Inquiry concerning Virtue, in two Diſcourſes: the firſt of Virtue, and the belief of a Deity; the ſecond, of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to Virtue. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Eſſay concerning the Power of the Magistrate, and the Rights of Mankind in Matters of Religion. With ſome Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in particular for the Diſſenters not being oblig'd to take the Sacramental Teſt but in their own Churches, and for a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Naturalization, Together with a Poſtſcript in anſwer to the Letter to a Convocation-man. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Stage condemn'd, and the Incouragement given to the Immoralities and Profaneneſs of the Theatre, by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Schools, Univerſities and Pulpits, cenſur'd; K. <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt's Sundays Mask and Declaration for Sports and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times on the Sabbath, largely related and animadverted on: The Arguments of all the Authors that have writ in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Stage againſt Mr. <hi>Collier,</hi> conſider'd: And the
<pb facs="tcp:32695:62"/>ſenſe of the Fathers, Councils, antient Philoſophers and Poets, the Greek and Roman States, and of the firſt Christian Emperors concerning die Drama, faithfully deliver'd; with other uſeful matters. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Detection of the Court and State of <hi>England</hi> during the four laſt Reigns, and the <hi>Interregnum;</hi> conſiſting of private Memoirs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With Obſervations and Reflections; and an <hi>Appendix</hi> diſcovering the preſent State of the Nation. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are many <hi>Secrets</hi> never before made publick as alſo a more impartial Account of the Civil Wars in <hi>England</hi> than has yet been given. By <hi>R. Coke</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> The 3d Edition very much corrected, with an Alphabetical Table. Price 7 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Complete Hiſtory of <hi>Europe,</hi> or a View of the Affairs thereof, Civil and Military, from the beginning of the Treaty of <hi>Nimeguen</hi> 1676. to the Peace concluded with the Turks 1699. including the Articles of the former, and the ſeveral Infringements of them; the Turkiſh Wars; the forming of the Grand Confederacy; the Revolution in <hi>England, &amp;c.</hi> With a particular Account of all the Actions by Sea and Land on both ſides; and the ſecret Steps that have been made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a Peace, both before as well as during the laſt Negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. Wherein are ſeveral Treaties at large. The whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termix'd with divers Original Letters, Declarations, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs never before publiſh'd. The 2d Edition corrected, and very much inlarg'd. Price 6 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Account of the firſt Voyages and Diſcoveries made by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> Containing the moſt exact Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hitherto publiſh'd, of their unparallel'd Cruelties on the <hi>Indians,</hi> in the deſtruction of above 40 Millions of People. Together with the Proporſitions offered to the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to prevent the further Ruin of the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> By <hi>Don Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew de las Caſas,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chiapa,</hi> who was an Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſs of their Cruelties. Illuſtrated with Cuts. To which is added, <hi>The Art of Travelling,</hi> ſhewing how a Man may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Travels to the beſt advantage. Price; 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The complete Gardner; or Directions for cultivating and right ordering of Fruit-gardens, and Kitchin-gardens. By Monſieur <hi>De La Quintinye.</hi> Now compendiouſly abridg'd, and made more uſeful, with very conſiderable Improvements. By <hi>George London,</hi> and <hi>Henry Wiſe.</hi> The ſecond Edition cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected. Price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Art of Memory: A Treatiſe uſeful for all, eſpecially ſuch as are to ſpeak in publick. The ſecond Edition. Price 12 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32695:63"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Rhetorica Anglorum, vel Exercitationes Oratoriae in Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam Sacram &amp; Communem. Quibus adjiciuntur quaedam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulae ad imbecilles memorias corroborandas. Omnia ad uſum &amp; in gratiam Academiarum &amp; Scholarum in Anglia compoſita.</hi> Approved und Recommended by the chief Maſters of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-taylors, Weſtminſter,</hi> and the <hi>Charter-houſe</hi> Schools. Price 18 <hi>d.</hi> Both by <hi>Marius D'Aſſigny</hi> B. D.</p>
            <p>A Rational and Speedy Method of attaining to the Latin Tongue. In 2 parts. The firſt containing ſuch Precepts as are common to all Languages: The ſecond what is more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the Latin Tongue. The whole being accommodated to the meaneſt Capacities, not only Perſons of riper years, but any Child that can read Engliſh, may by this method in a little time arrive to more knowledg than is uſually attain'd after ſeveral years drudgery in the common Road. Price 12 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Letter to his Majeſty K. <hi>William</hi> III. ſhewing, I. The Original Foundation of the Engliſh Monarchy. II. The Means by which it was removed from that Foundation. III. The Expedients by which it has bin ſupported ſince that Removal. IV. Its preſent Conſtitution as to all its integral parts. V. The beſt Means by which its Grandure may be for ever maintain'd. Price; 3 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Militia Reſorm'd, or an eaſy Scheme of furniſhing <hi>England</hi> with a conſtant Land Force, capable to prevent or to ſubdue any Foren Power, and to maintain perpetual Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et at home, without indangering the Public Liberty. Price 12 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſhort Hiſtory of Standing Armies in <hi>England,</hi> together with ſeveral other Pamphlets, ſhewing that a Standing Army is inconſiſtent with a Free Government.</p>
            <p>A Letter to a Member of Parliament, ſhewing that a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint on the Preſs is inconſiſtent with the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and dangerous to the Liberties of the Nation. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scotland</hi>'s Soveraignty aſſerted: being a Diſpute concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Homage, againſt thoſe who maintain that <hi>Scotland</hi> is a bee Liege of <hi>England,</hi> and that the King of <hi>Scots</hi> ows Homage to the King of <hi>England.</hi> Wherein are many judicious Reflec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on moſt of the Engliſh Hiſtorians who wrote before 1600. and ſeveral conſiderable Paſſages illuſtrating the Hiſtory of both Kingdoms. By Sir <hi>Tho. Craig,</hi> Author of the Book <hi>de Peudis.</hi> Tranſlated from the Latin Manuſcript, with a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face containing an account of the Author, and a Confutation of the Homage ſaid to be perform'd by <hi>Malcolm</hi> III. K. of <hi>Scots</hi> to <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor, found in the Archives of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and publiſh'd by Mr. <hi>Rimer.</hi> Price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
